<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most excellent and comfortable treatise, for all such as are any maner of way either troubled in minde or afflicted in bodie, made by Andrew Kingesmyl Gentleman, sometime fellowe of Alsolne Colledge in Oxforde. Whereunto is adioyned a verie godly and learned exhortation to suffer patiently al afflictions for the gospel of Christ Iesus. And also a conference betwixt a godly learned Christian [and] an afflicted conscie[n]ce: wherein, by the holy Scriptures the sleights of Satan are made manifest, and ouerthrowen: with a godly prayer thereunto annexed</title>
            <author>Kingsmill, Andrew, 1538-1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843130</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 441:11, 585:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most excellent and comfortable treatise, for all such as are any maner of way either troubled in minde or afflicted in bodie, made by Andrew Kingesmyl Gentleman, sometime fellowe of Alsolne Colledge in Oxforde. Whereunto is adioyned a verie godly and learned exhortation to suffer patiently al afflictions for the gospel of Christ Iesus. And also a conference betwixt a godly learned Christian [and] an afflicted conscie[n]ce: wherein, by the holy Scriptures the sleights of Satan are made manifest, and ouerthrowen: with a godly prayer thereunto annexed</title>
                  <author>Kingsmill, Andrew, 1538-1569.</author>
                  <author>Mills, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barkar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's "To the Christian reader" signed: F. mylles.</note>
                  <note>In three parts. Part 2 is 'A conference, containing a conflict had vvith Satan', with a separate dated titlepage and separate register; Part 3 is 'A forme of thankesgiuing and praier to be used of all godlie Christians in their families', with a caption title, colophon imprint and separate register.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴ [2d]A-C D⁴ A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Parts 2 and 3 formerly STC 21770.</note>
                  <note>Parts 2 and 3 identified as STC 21770 on UMI microfilm reel 585.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library (part 1 only) and the Folger Shakespeare Library (parts 2 and 3 only).</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 441 (Bodleian Library copy) and at reel 585 (Folger Shakespeare Library copy).</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>The final leaves of the 'Treatise' (sig. G4) and 'A forme of thankesgiuing' (sig. A8) are blanks.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7840:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7840:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A MOST Excellent and</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Treatiſe, for all ſuch as are any maner of way either trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>in minde or afflicted in bodie, Made by <hi>Andrew Kingeſmyl Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, ſometime fellowe of</hi> Alſolne Colledge <hi>in Oxforde.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is adioyned a verie</hi> godly and learned Exhortation to <hi>ſuffer patiently al afflictions for the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And alſo a conference betwixt a</hi> godly learned Chriſtian &amp; an afflicted conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: wherein, by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the ſleights of Satan are made manifeſt, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen: with a godly prayer thereunto annexed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London, by Chriſtopher Barkar. ANNO 1577.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7840:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7840:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING diuers papers and writings committed vnto me by a deare friend of myne, whom it pleaſed God not long ſince, after manie yeeres trauaile very profitably beſtowed in the miniſterie and preaching of the Goſpell, to call out of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, wretched and wicked world: And finding amongſt the ſaid writings this Treatiſe and the Exhortation annexed thereunto: I read both the one and the other all ouer, to mine owne great profite and comfort, I muſt needes confeſſe. And therefore perſwaded by mine owne experience in the reading of both theſe treatiſes, that the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of them in print might be no leſſe profitable and comfortable to many others, then to my ſelfe I founde them: I thought good not to holde them longer in my priuate cuſtodie as things dead and buried with the Authours, but to commit them to the Printer, ſo to haue them communicated to this Church of England, and as manie as vnderſtand the Engliſhe, to the prayſe and glorie of God for his gratious giftes in the writers, and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and inſtruction (I doubt not) of ſo many as ſhall reade them.</p>
            <p>Of the Authour of the Exhortation, I can ſay nothing more then that (as I coniecture by that he writeth) he liued in the late raigne of Q. Marie, being then an exile in foraine partes for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which at that time alſo was baniſhed from hence, as touching the open profeſſion thereof in
<pb facs="tcp:7840:3"/>
any common and publike places. And as for the matter of his Exhortation, I ſhall not neede to ſay anie more in commendation thereof to ſtirre men vp to the reading of it, then the bare title giuen to the ſame importeth: which with the ſhortneſſe of the Treatiſe it ſelfe may ſuffice to allure any godly and well diſpoſed perſon to peruſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>As touching the Authour of the Treatiſe whoſe name I haue expreſſed, though I could of him ſaye verie much to his great commendation, and that of mine owne knowledge, for that liuing together in one houſe we were long time and familiarlye acquainted: Yet I will for ſome reſpectes forbeare to prayſe him for his whole life and death, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thee to that which is briefly ſaid of him (and printed before) in a litle booke of his entituled, The view of mans eſtate, &amp;c: of which booke, though by an other name, him ſelfe maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this treatiſe: and had I knowen ſo much before the impreſſion thereof, as I coulde not, this comming ſo lately and long after to my handes, it ſhoulde haue borne no other name, then nowe I well perceyue the Authour him ſelfe called it by: though the title it nowe hath, be not (I truſt) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper and impertinent to the matter he handleth therein. To whom he writte this Treatiſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and vpon what occaſion, thou mayeſt eaſely perceyue if thou reade the whole all ouer: And though ſhee, to whome he writte the ſame be yet liuing, and the occaſion thereof ſuch as peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſome will miſlike of the publiſhing thereof: Yet being certainly perſwaded that neither the writer, if he were nowe liuing, or ſhe, to whom he writte, woulde haue any thing concealed for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
<pb facs="tcp:7840:3"/>
reſpectes, that may ſerue ſo well as this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe will (I am aſſured) to the edifying and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of manie: I haue aduentured to be a meane that it might be imprinted, with the approbation of ſuch as by good order in this behalfe are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to allowe of all ſuch matters to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, gentle Reader, accept in good part both this Treatiſe, and the Exhortation adioyned thereunto: which if they may ſerue for thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and comfort, as no doubt they will, thou haſt great cauſe to prayſe God both for the writers, and things by them written. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>f. mylles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7840:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A most Comfortable</hi> Treatiſe written by Andrew Kingeſmill <hi>to his ſiſter, very profitable for all men,</hi> eſpecially for ſuch as are any <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way afflicted in body</hi> or minde, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God forbid that I ſhould reioyce in any</hi> thing, but in the Croſſe of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, whereby the world is crucified vnto me, and I vnto the worlde.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare ſiſter in our Lord and</hi> Sauiour Chriſte Ieſus, wheras I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of your preſent ſtate and condition,<note place="margin">The cauſe that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Authour to wryte this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note> that it hath pleaſed God our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Father, ſomewhat to viſite &amp; touch you with his heauie hand, to chaſtize you with the rodde of his correction, and to lay vpon you ſome part of the croſſe of his Chriſt: Had I a farre better talent then I haue, which (God knowes) is but ſimple, yet I thought I could not any otherwiſe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſtowe &amp; occupie the ſame, then ſo, as it were, to lay it with you in exchange &amp; ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God to vtter vnto you ſome ſaying or ſentence, whereout you might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſome piece of relief or comfort: for this vſurie, and thoſe that haue any, ſo to occupie their talents, as to viſite the afflicted, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:7840:4"/>
the comfortleſſe, and to beſtow although as it were but one poore penie, to ſtrengthen the penſiue in patience,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.10</note> euen as our Sauiour commended the deuoute womans worke, for beſtowing her oyle vpon him toward his burial: So I doute not but this taſke which it hath pleaſed God now to ſet me, ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto him a lawful and gaineful vſurie, a wel beſtowed oyntment, and ſuch a worke, that as it lacketh not his charge, ſo it ſhal not be either to you fruitleſſe, either with him altogether thankeleſſe.<note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 12.15.</note> Reioyce with them that reioyce (ſayth the Apoſtle) and weepe with them that weepe.<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.34</note> And the ſonne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi> likewiſe, Let not them that weepe be without comfort, but mourne with ſuch as mourne. Now (Siſter) conſidering ſuch &amp; the like ſayings, calling to minde howe we haue reioyced together, enioying the good dayes, that God of his goodneſſe hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore giuen vs, and nothing doubting, but he will driue away thoſe ſtormie cloudes, and cauſe againe his cherefull ſunne to riſe and ſhine vpon vs: and (that which I can not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get) what a mourner you were w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me in the time of my mourning: verely now in the time of your diſtreſſe if my heauineſſe would eaſe you, or my ſorow might turne to your ioye,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:5"/>
I thinke my heart be not ſo harde, but that I ſhould beſtowe ſome teares vpon you, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that I foreſee mine owne portion in the worlde to be none other but paines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pleaſure.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> we reade lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted <hi>Sauls</hi> death, although one that ſought his bloud. And likewiſe <hi>Abſolon</hi> that wicked childe &amp; vnnatural ſonne, with what a fatherly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did he pitie his caſe? crying whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he heard the certaintie of his death, in ſuch ſort as is expreſſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 2. of <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. My ſonne <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> my ſonne, my ſonne <hi>Abſolon,</hi> would God I had died for thee: So verely ought our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and calamities to be common, and I eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially haue iuſte occaſion to beare the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then with you, being vnto me a true Siſter, a Siſter by naturall natiuitie, a Siſter by heauenly regeneration, one with whome I haue enioyed the ſweete, and who with me hath not refuſed the ſowre: wherefore as I cannot but with brotherly affection be ſorie for your ſadnes, ſo when I ſomewhat lift vp mine eyes toward heauen, &amp; haue in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the infinite mercies and marueilous working of God our heauenly Father, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his choſen children and ſanctified Sainctes here on earth, then (me thinkes) I receiue ſo plentifull ioye of ſpirit, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:7840:5"/>
of patience againſt thoſe ſtormes and tempeſtes of aduerſities and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which I know I haue in the way of my pilgrimage to paſſe, and which I know by the courſe of Gods working abyde certainly for all true &amp; ſtedfaſt Chriſtians, that in vttering the ſame vnto you it may be I ſhall giue you ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of comfort. God therefore I beſeeche him guide my hand, and direct my heart, and ſo beholde you with his Fatherly eye, and cherefull countenance, that we may both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort of his holy Spirit the true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, promiſed by our Sauiour, that we may reioyce one with another, and both in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now there are diuers meanes that God hath ordeined &amp; prouided for the cheriſhing and refreſhing of heauie heartes and ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoules:<note place="margin">Comforts, ſome are temporall, ſome eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> for ſome there are which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the bodie, as earthly and temporall, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerne the minde, as Ghoſtly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual, which wheras they are to be had,<note place="margin">Temporal comforts.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them are to be refuſed, foraſmuch as God therein with our vſe and commoditie, looketh to reape the fruite of his owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> alloweth <hi>Timothie</hi> and counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him for his weake ſtomaks ſake mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to drinke wyne: and <hi>Salomon</hi> lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:6"/>
Giue the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g drinke vnto him that is readie to periſhe,<note place="margin">Prou. 31.6</note> and wine vnto them that haue griefe of hearte. Concerning theſe, although they be ſomewhat beſides my care, yet this I may truely ſaye, that you haue to thanke God with a moſt chereful ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath not left you ſo deſtitute in this behalf, as he hath thouſands of other our brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Meate &amp; drink, &amp;c.</note>Howe many are there, not far from you, if you liſt (as I thinke you doe) to beholde them, and conſider them with ſome compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, in reſpect of whom you muſt nedes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your ſelfe and happie handmaid of God: as whoſe hope is their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, patience their pleaſure, their wine a cuppe of colde water, and whom for their apparel, neceſſitie allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no more then their bare naked ſkin? how many poore Lazars are there that would be glad to gather vp the crummes vnder that table, where your hand is free without grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging? You ſay peraduenture ſometimes in your fit, I am a miſerable woman: But what may they ſaye, that haue neither cloth nor clout to defend them from the bitter byting colde? what may they ſay, which many times haue neither bitte of bread, neither droppe of drinke, wherewith to ſatiſfie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> griedie worme of hunger, or to quenche the drie diſeaſe of
<pb facs="tcp:7840:6"/>
thirſt? How many are there, which in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of you, and me although peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the leaſte of xiiii, who being driuen to the draffe of hogges, may ſay with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal ſonne, In how farre better caſe are the hired ſeruantes of that houſe, then we ſeely ſoules are? doutleſſe hauing as we haue, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we did get it hardly, &amp; buye it deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet ſhould we be in farre better ſtate then a great number, which by experience knowe what the want of thoſe neceſſaries are, which God of his gratious goodnes hath with a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall hand, beſtowed on vs his euill deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeruantes: and who for any thing to be ſene in our ſelues, deſerue as euill and worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many of thoſe nedy naked ſoules, which at ſundrie times faint for want of foode, &amp; as the bare beaſtes ſtand open to all winde and weather, ſubiect to all aduentures, free from no aduerſitie. <hi>Dauid</hi> well conſidered theſe benefites of God, which we, becauſe that we haue not felt the lacke of them, make litle ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of. God ſatiſfieth ſaith he,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.9</note> the thirſtie ſottle, and filleth the hungrie ſoule with good things: and numbring diuers other the like benefites, which Gods people dayly receiue at his hande, hee crieth out twiſe or thryſe with earneſt zeale, O that men woulde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:7840:7"/>
before the Lord his louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and his wonderous workes before the ſonnes of men: Let vs likewiſe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the goodnes of God toward vs in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Kinsfolkes &amp; friends.</note>And me thinkes (Siſter) if theſe outward earthly thinges may anie thing make in the matter, you haue iuſt cauſe to reioyce. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> you know complaineth often times that his familiars and kindred ſtarted from him in his aduerſitie, for beſide the multitude of his enemies, which as he maketh his accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t were more then heares vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head, he ſaith alſo,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.8.</note> I am become a ſtranger vnto my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, euen an aliant vnto my mothers ſons: In another place, he vttereth as a part of his griefe, that he was bereft of his Father and Mother: Concerning thoſe pointes you are not ſo farre in as <hi>Dauid</hi> was: you haue bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, you haue ſiſters, I know, that account your caſe their common caſe. That God hath viſited our Father, I craue as great part of that plague as the beſt or the worſt of you: that God hath ſo preſerued our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the mirrour of al mothers, therein you haue as great part as the beſt of vs. As for open enemies that ſeeke your hinderance, or that reioyce at your aduerſitie, I know none
<pb facs="tcp:7840:7"/>
you haue: but you know your ſelf a number of your friends, that vnfainedly wiſhe your proſperitie.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour, you may remember, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that the Foxes had holes where to couch them,<note place="margin">A houſe or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place.</note> and the birdes of the aire haue their place of reſt, but the Sonne of man had not where to hide his head. O that we could, that we would compare our ſelues in our aduerſities with our Sauiour, the Sonne of man, the verie Sonne of God, of him to learne patience: then no doubt but by him we ſhould receiue comfort. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider therfore the goodnes of God, how he hath prouided for vs by the gentlenes of our deare Mother, a place which we vſe as an home and habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that no Foxe hole, but thankes be to God a warme and wel feathered neſte, where we haue free egreſſe and regreſſe.</p>
            <p>This ſcripture was fulfilled in our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,<note place="margin">Concord of brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> They of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s owne houſe are his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and he thereof complaining ſaide, He that eateth bread with mee hath lift vp his heele againſt me: but thankes be vnto our heauenly Father, who hath ioyned our houſe in ſuch an vnitie, that we do not (as farre as I ſee) one diſdeine the other in neceſſities and aduerſities, neither enuie ech other in things
<pb facs="tcp:7840:8"/>
ſucceeding proſperouſly. God of his mercie grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that band long to continue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of <hi>Sidmountaine,</hi> that it may deſerue the commendation of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> euen to be as a Citie which is at peace within it ſelf.<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.3</note> This was it whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> receiued much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that after great diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, God had grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his kingdome the peace and concorde of his people, ſo he ſaith of his experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how good a thing it is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1</note> and how come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for brethren to dwell euen together. He compareth it vnto the precious oyntment powred on the head, that ſpreadeth abroad to the refreſhing of the whole bodie, and vnto the dewe of <hi>Hermon,</hi> and that which falleth vpon the mountaines of <hi>Sion,</hi> places ryche and fruitfull both with temporal benefites, &amp; with the ſpirituall bleſſings of God. This cherefull oyle and freſhe dewe of vnitie and concord betwixt you, your brethren, ſiſters and friendes, God hath bleſſed you withall: ſuche dewe falleth not in all places, ſuch oyle is not to be found in al houſes, the freſh flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of vnitie and amitie is not to be found in euerie fielde: but this as it groweth greene in the Garden of <hi>Sidmountaine,</hi> which if it fade, then farewell my part: but now flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing as it doth by the gratious goodneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:7840:8"/>
of God, me thinke you ſhould not but reioyce in the Lord, who hath reſerued vnto you this piece of Paradiſe, that you may haue the full fruition of that beautiful and ſweet ſmelling flowre of concord. Thus I haue endeuoured ſomewhat to lead you into the conſideration of the temporall benefites and bleſſings of God beſtowed vpon you, whereout it may be you ſhal pick ſome piece of comfort, if things worldly and earthly, outward and temporall, may make any thing in this medicine. But it may be, that as to the ſicke, things otherwiſe ſweete become ſowre &amp; vnſauerie, and to the weake and ſickely ſtomake, the ſweet hony is lothſome: ſo the mothe of penſiuenes hath entered your heart, that theſe weaker medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines may not haue their full force, and due operation.</p>
            <p>Nowe after that you haue ſtoode on this place, to ſee and looke about you what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is to be had on earth, where you may well eſpie more then I haue ſhewed you: hencefoorthe (Siſter) let vs get on the mounting wynge of fayth,<note place="margin">Euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forts.</note> let vs rayſe our ſelues vp through the clouds, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, let vs come from the foteſtoole of God to his glorious ſeate, and that cannot be but comfortable vnto vs to conſider.<note place="margin">Reue. 4.4.</note> For <hi>S. Iohn</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7840:9"/>
(as he deſcribeth his viſion) when he ſaw the Maieſtie of God ſitting on his glorious throne, declareth that the throne of God is compaſſed about with a rainbow, a ſure ſeale and token of Gods mercie towards vs, that although he often times raine vpon vs, yet he wil no more drowne vs. This hath euer bene the chief comfort of the godly in al their diſtreſſes and afflictions, they all had an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial eye this way: Reade you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 121. <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 123. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> there to conſider the practiſe of the Prophet, how he looked toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne of God. I will lift mine eyes to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines (ſaith he) from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce mine helpe ſhall come, mine helpe commeth from the Lord which hath made heauen and earth, &amp;c. I lift mine eyes to thee that dwelleſt in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens: beholde, as the eyes of an handmayde marke the eyes of her miſtres, ſo our eyes wayte vpon the Lord our God, vntill he haue mercie vpon vs. Now then (Siſter) laying aſide all earthly conſiderations, if they will not worke with you, let vs looke vpon that helpe that commeth from heauen.</p>
            <p>This as I remember is one amongſt the wiſe ſayings of <hi>Salomon:</hi> Heauines caſteth downe the hearte of man, but a good worde rayſeth it vp againe: If any mans worde
<pb facs="tcp:7840:9"/>
or wiſedome may any thing herein preuaile, then eſpecially the good word of God,<note place="margin">Gods worde.</note> which as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth is mighty in operation. It is ſo ful of comfort, that if grace wanted not to vtter and receiue it accordingly, I nothing doubte but if you were halfe dead, it would ſoone quicken and ſet you vpright againe.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> So ſayth <hi>S. Paul,</hi> whatſoeuer is written, is written for our learning, that we through comfort and pacience of the Scriptures, might haue hope. Seing then the Lord hath left vs this heauenly treaſure here on earth, euen to our ſo great commoditie thereby to learne patience, and receiue comfort, let vs vſe theſe as our ſpectacles to behold the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, which of our ſelues being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but blindeneſſe it ſelfe, are not able to ſearche out or to ſee: and this ſhalbe as your diet, that you reſort to thoſe ſweete running ryuers, ſpringing vp vnto eternall life, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling and aduiſing you, here to laye out the whole line of your life: no day, nor houre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth amiſſe, but in the Scriptures you may find comfort: Yea, there ye ſhall meete with the fountaine of all comfort, the Spirit of God chering and cheriſhing you after a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and marueylous maner. Preſently for my part, I chiefly commit your cauſe to his
<pb facs="tcp:7840:10"/>
cure, and by his grace, I ſhall endeuour to giue you ſome taſte of that precious liquour: God graunt it be not marred for lacke of a better veſſell.</p>
            <p>Firſt therfore, I am perſuaded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dout of your adoption and election in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Election in Chriſt.</note> that your name is entred in the booke of life, and that you are ſurely ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp for a ſaued ſanctified ſoule. This foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation being layd on ſo ſure a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, hauing our hands faſtened on this hold, what ſtorms or floods of affliction may there ariſe, but we may (conſidering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tender mercy of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his choſen children) endure with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, ouercome with comfort, and wade thorowe with ioy, knowing ſure we ſhal haue a day, and ſeeing certainely although a farre of, the quiet and glorious hauen we haue to arriue at? It is a moſt comfortable ſaying which the Apoſtle vttereth vnto you:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> We knowe (ſaith he) that all things worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the beſte vnto them that loue God, euen to them that are called of his purpoſe. This one ſentence ſo ſetting foorth the care that God your heauenly Father hath ouer you, might ſatiſfie you, if you could weigh it as it is worthie.</p>
            <p>Great and manifolde were the miſeries
<pb facs="tcp:7840:10"/>
which that choſen of God ſuffered, reade you the 11. of the 2. to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paul.</note> You ſhal finde there at what hard meat, &amp; how ſowre ſauce the Lord ſet that his paineful and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant: as ſtripes, perilles both on Sea and land, euill entreatie both of the <hi>Iewe</hi> and the <hi>Gentile,</hi> the deceit of falſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, painfulneſſe, watching, hunger, thirſt, colde, nakedneſſe, and all kinde of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet he hauing that confidence and ſtedfaſt perſwaſion of the eternal prouidence of God, that he turneth all things to the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his electe, euen in the middeſt of theſe miſeries he ſhewed a moſt chereful ſpirit, as hee ſaith numbring many kindes of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> in all theſe thinges we are more then conquerours, by him that loued vs.</p>
            <p>In what diſtreſſe thinke you was that iuſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> being endangered to periſh in the pit,<note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note> throwne in by the handes of his owne bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">Gen. 37.24.</note> and afterwarde ſolde of them into a ſtrange countrey, where alſo being taken of ſuſpicion to haue abuſed his Maſter <hi>Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phars</hi> wyfe, was caſt into priſon: yet he alſo ouer theſe and the like temptations,<note place="margin">Gen. 39.20</note> became in time a conquerour, well perceiuing in the ende, that it was the Lordes doing to ſome good ende, although he did not ſtraight vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb facs="tcp:7840:11"/>
the ſame. And therefore beſides his owne comfort, he quieted alſo the troubled mindes of his brethren, declaring vnto them the prouidence of God, wheron he wholy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended.<note place="margin">Gen. 45.4, 5.</note> I am <hi>Ioſeph</hi> your brother (ſayth he) whom ye ſolde into <hi>Egypt:</hi> now therefore be not ſadde, nor grieued with your ſelues that you ſolde me hither, for God did ſend me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for your preſeruation: neyther did hee ſo much attend the fact of his brethren, as the prouidence of God in the matter, ſo that he ſeemeth in reſpect flatly to denie that they had done ought in the matter:<note place="margin">Gen. 45.8.</note> as in theſe wordes, Now then you ſent me not hither, but God who hath made me a Father vnto <hi>Pharao,</hi> and Lord ouer all his houſe, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler throughout all the land of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And by this meanes and conſiderations, God gaue him that he made the leſſe accompt of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his parentes, the ingratitude of his brethren, the lack of his countrey, and alſo the ſlaunderous and vniuſt impriſonement.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Dauid</hi> beeing in flight for the feare of his owne ſonne <hi>Abſolon,</hi> heard, and bare with patience, rayling <hi>Shimei,</hi> taking as it were his pleaſure of him in his aduerſitie, throwing ſtones at him as though hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no more of him then of a vyle dog,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:11"/>
curſing and calling him murderer: &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Abiſhai</hi> his courage ſerued him to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge <hi>Dauids</hi> quarrel, and would haue fet his head,<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> if that he would haue but ſaid the worde: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the humilitie, the patience of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the comfort of a King, verely he lifted vp his eyes to the hill, the holy hill of God, from whence he was aſſured all thoſe things proceeded, to ſome commoditie and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his: wherfore this was his anſwere to <hi>Abiſhai</hi> that ſought reuengement, he cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me, euen becauſe the Lorde hath bidden him curſe <hi>Dauid.</hi> This was the holde and handfaſt, that that princely Prophete tooke wherewith to ſtaye him ſelf, euer depending vpon the prouidence of his liuing God. He knewe that whatſoeuer befell him, God had a ſtroke in it, yea and further, being fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the mercie of God, he knewe moſt aſſuredly thoſe chaſtiſements and correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould turne him to God, as he maketh proteſtation, in the 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> It is good for me that I haue bene afflicted: ſo that beſide his pacience and comfort he accompted it a gaine, and none of the ſmaleſt benefites of God, that he was ſo corrected at his iuſt and mercifull hand.</p>
            <p>You may alſo conſider the example of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:7840:12"/>
               <hi>Iob:</hi> How he waded through his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as who knowing that all thoſe hils of miſerie, fell vpon him, no otherwiſe then by the determinate appointment of the moſt hieſt, with the conſideration thereof he refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed himſelfe, after that all worldly ſuccours and comforts were taken from him, and ſo became a conquerour ouer all the grieuous aſſaultes of Satan, as who, he was aſſured, could go no further then he had his limittes appointed and aſſigned vnto him, by the iuſt ruling and mercifull diſpoſing hand of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerliuing God: wherfore he made it no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of miſfortune (as we commonly do in the like caſes) that his cattel were made a praye for his enemies, that his ſonnes &amp; daughters had that ſtrange ende, the houſe falling on their heads: but by ſuch his words he openly ſheweth the inward comfort of his hearte, The Lord hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, as it pleaſed the Lord ſo is it come to paſſe, bleſſed be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Name of the Lord: &amp; by this we vnderſtand that he had not ſo much regard of his enemies the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and the <hi>Sabeans,</hi> whome he knewe to be but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Deuill the chiefe worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but alwayes had his eye ſtedfaſtly bent vpon God his Creator and redeemer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:7840:12"/>
whoſe ordinance and appointment, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them could haue any whit mooued or preuailed againſt him, no more then the ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe winde had power of it ſelfe, ſo to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe the houſe vpon his children. And for as much as he was the ſeruant of God, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured himſelfe, that Satan with his ſlaues could not doe or intend him ſo much hurt, but his Lorde and God woulde euen by the ſame meanes turne it to his great furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance &amp; commoditie, as we are giuen to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of the hiſtorie that God did in deede perfourme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: So that by this he became ſo humble and patient, ſo ſtedfaſt in hope, that he ſaid, that if the Lords pleaſure were to kill him, to take his life from him, yet would he not let go his holde, giue ouer his hope, or blaſpheme the Name of God, to the which he was marueilouſly prouoked.</p>
            <p>Behold likewiſe the behauiour &amp; courage of thoſe three noble yong men whom <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonozor</hi> threatened the terrible fire,<note place="margin">Three chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the fornace.</note> for that they refuſed to worſhip his golden god: ſee how they take holde on the mercie, and prouident care of God their Lord. For thus they anſwered the King, Beholde, our God whom we ſerue is able to deliuer vs from the hote firie fornace, &amp; he wil deliuer vs out of
<pb facs="tcp:7840:13"/>
thine hand (O King.) But if not, be it kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to thee (O King) that we wil not ſerue thy gods, nor do worſhippe to thy golden I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, which thou haſt ſet vp: and according to that their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant hope and faith, the Lord fayleth not, as you know, marueilouſly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Daniel.</note>And what other comfort had their fellow <hi>Daniel</hi> being encloſed to be deuoured of the Lyons in the Denne?<note place="margin">Dan. 6.16. &amp;c.</note> according to whoſe hope, likewyſe the Lorde ſent his Angel to ſhut and mouzle vp the Lyons mouthes, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him harmleſſe. The Scripture yeldeth plentifull ſtore of the like examples and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whereout if we ſtand to conſider them, we haue inough ſo to arme vs againſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures, that no tribulation, no anguiſh may bee ſo extreme, but that by patience we may ouercome them, no calamities ſo great or grieuous, but that they are to be conquered by comfort of the Scriptures. So ſayth the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> God is faithfull which wil not ſuffer you to bee tempted aboue your power, but will euen giue the iſſue with the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that you may bee able to beare them: where he ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth the afflicted among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and doth ſtrengthen them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the croſſe, leading them no farther then
<pb facs="tcp:7840:13"/>
into the conſideration of Gods eternall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, which maketh the ſharpe and the ſowre, ſoft and ſweete in the ende,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.11</note> although no maner of chaſtiſement (as he ſaith) is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the preſent time. I haue in thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer examples according to my ſimplicitie, ſent you ſome of the righteous and tried ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, to ſtand you in ſteade of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries and Surgeons, of whom you may learne to cure your wound without douting, foraſmuch as they miniſter you euen ſuch ſoueraigne medicines, as they them ſelues haue taſted and tried (as you ſee) to their end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe comfort: but yet the chief phiſition is to come,<note place="margin">Chriſt.</note> Chriſt Ieſus (I meane) the ſalue of all our ſores, the paterne of al patience, and moſt aſſured comfort of all ſorowing ſoules, and readie redreſſe in all aduerſities. You haue ſeene in the examples afore, the experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of good ſouldiours fighting a good fight, and how they haue quitte themſelues againſt the temptations of the worlde, and the aſſaultes of Satan: Nowe turne your eyes towarde Chriſt our redemer the great Captaine, and moſt renowmed conquerour of all that euer taſted theſe worldly infirmities, whoſe euill entreatie and hard handling the time ſerueth not now to deſcribe vnto you, but I ſend you
<pb facs="tcp:7840:14"/>
to the head ſpring, the hiſtorie of the Goſpel: you may alſo at your leaſure reade that mine exerciſe concerning the loue of God,<note place="margin">This is ſince imprinted and called, The viewe of the eſtate of man, &amp;c. <hi>Philip 2.5.6.7.8.</hi>
               </note> where I haue aſſayed to ſay ſomewhat to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Onely now I giue you <hi>S. Pauls</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Let the ſame minde be in you which was euen in Chriſte Ieſus, who being the Sonne of God, and very God, one with his Father, made himſelf of no reputation, tooke on him the forme of a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he humbled him ſelfe and became obedient vnto the death, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the death of the croſſe. Here learne of your Sauiour, patience and humilitie, and marke where lay his comfort, verely that way that other his ſaued ſoules haue ſought, euen the prouidence of his God, and by him our God his Father, &amp; (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to him) our Father: for ſo he ſaid when that loſt childe went out from him and his other diſciples to worke his purpoſed treaſon, Verely (ſaith he) it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the ſonne of man, as it is written of him: and at this marke he ſeemed to ayme, when as <hi>Pilate</hi> vaunted himſelfe and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed ouer him, ſaying, that he had power to crucifie him, and likewiſe to looſe him: then our Sauiours anſwere was, thou couldeſt haue no power againſt me, except it were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thee from aboue. So when he did with
<pb facs="tcp:7840:14"/>
deepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration as it were aforehand, taſte the bitterneſſe of his cuppe, this way he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out of his temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying to his father, thy will be fulfilled and not myne: this was his comfort in the extremities of the croſſe,<note place="margin">Act. 2.26, 27.</note> and his fleſh alſo reſted in this hope, that the Lord would not ſuffer his holy one to ſee corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. By theſe you may be ſufficiently ſtored with diuerſe kinde of medicines, you haue both the gentle and the ſtrong working be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
            <p>The next care concerneth the vſe hereof,<note place="margin">The apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note> that they be applied and placed to the ſore. Now therefore if you wil ſet theſe glaſſes of the afflicted ſeruants of God, and eſpecially Chriſt crucified before your eyes, I doubt not but that it ſhall quicken all the dead fleſh that lieth about your heart. For firſt if you wil compare quantitie with quantitie, ſurely yours may ſeeme but an April ſhowre in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of theſe bloudie floudes and ſeas of ſorowes that paſſed ouer their heads. But make your caſe comparable with others the aforeſaid (as peraduenture it is more then I am aware of) yet being grounded on Chriſt Ieſus with ſtedfaſt faith, hauing your elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion certaine by your honeſt conuerſation in the works of light, and the Spirit of adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:7840:15"/>
bearing witnes with your ſpirit that you are a choſen childe of God, hauing in iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the iuſt dealing and mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God towardes his veſſels prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to honour, although in your ſelfe you be humbled (as neceſſarie it is) yet in God you cannot but reioyce and glorie with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and Saintes on the earth. Were it ſo that men reuiled you as <hi>Shimei</hi> did <hi>Dauid,</hi> why ſhould you not content &amp; quiet your ſelf as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, ſaying, the Lord hath ſent him for this purpoſe? yea, whatſoeuer kinde of croſſe it ſhall pleaſe God to viſite vs withall, we ought by his example to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the good purpoſe of God therein, &amp; to ſay, It is good for vs that we taſte of ſome trouble,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.8.</note> leſt we be found for baſtard children (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh.) If you had ſuſteined loſſe of frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, parents, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or huſbands, ſtanding at one ſtaye with <hi>Iob,</hi> then for your comfort you haue to ſay, The Lord hath giuen, the Lorde hath taken away. Let the caſe be (I am ſure it is not ſo ill) that you were peſtered with <hi>Iobs</hi> miſerable diſeaſe, as wee are all in the hands of God, vpon vs to worke his wil, and there is neither of both vndoutedly, but haue deſerued far worſe then iuſt <hi>Iob:</hi> yet he hath prouided for vs before hand a ſtaffe to ſtaye
<pb facs="tcp:7840:15"/>
on, and hath giuen vs a leſſon of patience in that anſwere which he made his wyfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking him to yelde to the aſſault of Satan, and to blaſpheme his God: Thou ſpeakeſt like a fooliſh woman (ſaith he) ſhall wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue good at the hand of God, &amp; not receiue euill? If you had loſt your countrey, which now you enioye by the benefit of God, might you not well conceiue with your ſelfe of the will and worke of God therein, to ſome ſuch purpoſe as he wrought by <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſale and banniſhment? whereſoeuer you ſhall come, whatſoeuer entertainement or entreatie you ſhould finde, would you not ſay as he did, it is God that hath ſent me hither? Suppoſe you were in the pit with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> in the de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne with <hi>Daniel,</hi> or that you made vp the meſſe with thoſe three appointed to the fyer, <hi>Sidrach, Miſach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego:</hi> would you miſtruſt now eſpecially that they haue made the waye before you, but that God would prouide ſome iſſue for you in the middeſt of theſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, either to ſaue you harmleſſe by a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deliuerance, or els as it ſhould be beſt for you to make you a conquerour by patience?</p>
            <p>And to come to Chriſt that fountaine of all conſolation for all Chriſtians: O Siſter,<note place="margin">Chriſts to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> we neuer felt with our litle finger that fyer
<pb facs="tcp:7840:16"/>
wherein he was conſumed for our ſinnes, we haue not taſted with the typ of our tongue, that bitter cuppe, wherein he ſwallowed vp death due vnto vs for our offences: wee ſleepe in whole ſkinnes, his hands, his feete, his ſydes were pearced of merciles murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: we for the moſt part haue eaſe and reſt, he found no place on earth where to reſt his head: we thinke much if we be ſomewhat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed with a litle paine or griefe of bodie, he ſwet and ſhed bloudie water to eaſe vs, and releaſe vs of perpetuall paines. Nowe then (Siſter) thruſt in your finger with <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle, and feele with faith the bloudie woundes of your ſauiour and redemer: and theſe being conſidered, what are our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt griefes, but fleabites in compariſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that inward anguiſhe and paſſion of the ſoule, farre paſſing his outwarde apparent pangues, whereby he felt the ſeuere iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and wrath of God, the rewarde of our euil deſerts? Come you hither (Siſter) with your heauie burthen and here refreſh you, for here is the well and the water of life, receiue you hence the moſt comfortable <hi>aqua vite,</hi> ſtilling downe from the croſſe of oure redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and peacemaker Chriſt Ieſus the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. God hath laide vpon you ſome kinde
<pb facs="tcp:7840:16"/>
of croſſe, but none ſuch as his owne Sonne your Sauiour hath borne before you, God hath thought good for ſome purpoſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his glorie, to put you to ſome pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: O why ſhould you or any of vs grudge to take on vs the yoke of God? he hath not ſpared his deare and onely Sonne, to make him a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a ſeruant, a ſacrifice for our ſoules redemption, which were once ſolde vnder ſinne, the ſlaues of Satan. But were it (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie were you if it were ſo in deede) that you had to pledge your ſauiour where he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun vnto you, if that you hong on the croſſe together with him, had you not then comfort enough by you: could you not well content your ſelfe to be baptized with his baptiſme, whoſe handmaid, I know you will not denie your ſelfe to be? is it not enough for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to be ſerued as his maſter? were you in the place of the penitent theefe, crauing his pardon as he did hang together with our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, would you haue deſpaired, would you haue miſtruſted, might you be comfortleſſe, would you not reioyce?</p>
            <p>But you will ſay he had his Sauiour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent before his eyes. But O you of litle faith, if you haue not as good aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mercy as he: do you not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that by the iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:7840:17"/>
of our Iudge, they are moſt bleſſed which beleue and ſee not? But he happie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heard thoſe ioyfull wordes at his redemers mouth, To daie thou ſhalt bee with me in paradiſe.<note place="margin">Warrants out of the ſcriptures for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</note> And is that ſufficient? why then haue not you as ſure an obligation, the warrant of his word, his teſtament ſealed with his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud? or els are you left out of that will? Doth he not ſay vnto you as directly as to any other, Come vnto me and I ſhall refreſh you? Doth he not ſay vnto you, Aſke and haue, ſeeke and find, knocke and it ſhall be opened? are you not aſſured of that abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the daye of the Lord his appearance, Thy faith hath ſaued thee,<note place="margin">Mar. 7.29.</note> goe thy waye in peace? are you not to be numbred among them to whom it ſhalbe ſaid, Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my father?<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.16.</note> when that Chriſt ſaith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, he that beleueth hath euerlaſting life: when that he ſaieth, I bring the water of life, I am the bread of life, I am the vine, you are the braunches: I am the good ſhepherd, the true Meſſias, the redemer of the worlde, the phyſition of the ſicke, comming to ſaue that which is loſt: in al theſe can you not picke out that promiſe to be with him in paradiſe? I dare not doubt (Siſter) that you are to ſeeke concerning theſe thinges, you haue (I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:7840:17"/>
miſtruſt) laide the foundation of your fayth on Chriſt the right rocke of ſaluation: then can you no more doubte, then if you had the poſſeſſion of paradiſe alreadie, euen as it was prepared for you from the beginning, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he made the graunt, that hath the whole matter in his handes, and in whome there is no guile. Stand therfore, ſtand ſtiffe and fall not, let not go this handfaſt, which if you doe, no winde or weather may riſe in the worlde that ſhall any whit moue you or your ſo ſure building,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.4</note> ſtanding on ſo good a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and ſo ſounde a rocke. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in his firſt epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, ſetting Chriſt Ieſus before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whom he writeth, This we write vnto you (ſaith he) that your ioy might be full. Verely (Siſter) if we coulde fully conſider Chriſt with his mercie and merites, our heartes might not but be filled vp full with ioy: for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſowre, but in Chriſt it becommeth ſweete and ſauourie, there is no want of any earthly thing, but Chriſt ſupplieth with a greater meaſure. The braunches that abide in that vine, no weather may make them to wither: and although they ſeeme for a ſeaſon much like to the naturall vine, to be as drie and rotten ſtickes, ſuch as men would ſcarce gather vp in the way, yet the heauenly huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman
<pb facs="tcp:7840:18"/>
ſo cheriſheth and tendereth them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in time which he knoweth to be moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, euen then they ſhal ſhew themſelues in their kinde, and freſhly flouriſhe in their fruits, when all other flowers are faded, and other trees which are not planted by him may not longer ſtand for their rotten roots.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſweres to certain obiections co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the want of things.</note>Let vs therefore ſtand a litle and ſee what more comfort we may ſucke out of that freſh and fruitfull vine, ſo ſhall our hearts receiue ioye, and our ioye ſhalbe full. You haue no landes, nor liuinges (I thinke) in deede any thing ſuperfluous, but yet competent. and if you were much more needie, euen vtterly deſtitute, yet you haue not to take great thought for the matter, ſeeing Chriſt telleth you, you ſhall haue life euerlaſting, paradiſe is your inheritance, his owne kingdome is your poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie.</note>Companie in deede is comfortable: but be it that you were berefte of the companie and comfort of your brethren and ſiſters, yet the true Chriſtian cannot be ſolitary.<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.7</note> 
               <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith, If we walke in the light as he walked, we haue felowſhip with him. And he him ſelfe ſaieth, he will not leaue vs comfortleſſe or ſolitarie, yea he wilbe preſent with vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worldes ende, that is, with all his, at al
<pb facs="tcp:7840:18"/>
times ſending vs the Comforter his holy ſpirit. If we do that which he commaundeth vs, then he accompteth vs his friendes, his brethren, his ſiſters, and that which is chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, becauſe it is endleſſe, after we haue ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne out our courſe, we ſhalbe with him in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, making continually that prayer for vs vnto his Father, which he began here on earth, Father I will that they which thou haſt giuen me be with me where I am, that they may beholde my glorie.</p>
            <p>Beholde,<note place="margin">Worldly eſtimation</note> you ſhall beholde the glorie of Chriſt: what then will you take thought for any piece of worldly eſtimation? All the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of man (ſaith the Prophet) is as the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the fielde, ſone ripe, ſone rotten, but the crowne of glorie, which you ſhall receiue by Chriſt, is incorruptible, once founde, neuer loſte, once ripe, neuer rotten: what neede you paſſe vpon the wicked earthly Mammon, whereas you be moſt aſſured of that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure laied vp for your ſtore in heauen, euen Chriſt Ieſus the riches of the riche, and high God of heauen?</p>
            <p>It would be a comfort for you peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Mariage.</note> to haue an head and huſband to defende you, &amp; in whom you might delite as in your owne ſoule, by whom you might haue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb facs="tcp:7840:19"/>
of godly children, vnto many in deede the verye bleſſing of God: but in this alſo you muſt ſubmitte your ſelfe to the mightie hande of God, knowing that he worketh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe wayes in diuerſe veſſels, and thoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to honour, for to ſome mariage is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, to ſome it bringeth ioy and gladnes: but contrarily in many you may ſee it is a ſnare of the worlde, a ſtumbling blocke, and plaine diuorcement betwixt God and them. And this inconuenience I knowe commeth not of mariage it ſelfe, as the proper and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal cauſe, which God hath ordained as holy and comfortable: but by their abuſe, and for their iuſt plague. Whereas ſome ſucke hony, ſome other meete with gall, and venyme: and yet the flower beautifull enough, and goodly in the eye. Wherefore God of his high wiſedome, knowing much better what is good for vs then we for our ſelues, doth at ſundrie times cut vs ſhort from the fruition of many his good creatures, benefites and ordinances, leaſt by abuſe we ſhould in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner turne the nature of them to our owne hinderance and confuſion, ſo that it may bee better for vs to lacke them then to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Diuerſe I thinke there be good men, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt maydens, which peraduenture would be
<pb facs="tcp:7840:19"/>
hard huſbandes, and ſhrewd wiues: neither would it be any ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge caſe to ſee, that ſome bare the firſt yoke honeſtly and godly, which at the ſecond match ouerrule &amp; weary their yoke fellows, cauſing them with repentance to wiſhe their former libertie againe. Such is the diuerſe working of God, that in ſome he is better pleaſed with mariage, and other he holdeth in ſingle life as moſt expedient for them.</p>
            <p>Some againe he bleſſeth with the fruite of children,<note place="margin">Barennes.</note> other he maketh baren and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, yet both for the better, both ſeruing to the glorie of God, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Looke on the compariſon made by <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the 4. of the book of wiſdome: he ſaith, that barennes is better with vertue, then to haue a multitude of children. Neither doe I write this as one that deſpaireth of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie this way: I know you haue had good offers, which by iudgement of man, might haue bene conuenient for you to haue follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but I haue tolde you the worſte, and yet nothing doubting but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt is to come. <hi>Anna</hi> you may remember mentioned in the firſt of <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. the wife of <hi>Elkanah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anna.</note> the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie handmaid of God, how he exerciſed her a long time in patience with the ſhame of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:20"/>
as it was cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in thoſe dayes. But the Lorde when hee had brought her lowe enough, then he rayſed her againe, heard her humble petition, and gaue her for her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that iuſte Iudge her ſonne <hi>Samuel,</hi> his true ſeruant.<note place="margin">Tob. 3.10.</note> In the hiſtorie of <hi>Tobias,</hi> we reade in what diſtreſſe that humble mayden <hi>Sara</hi> was,<note place="margin">Sara.</note> whom it pleaſed God to viſite, and chaſtiſe her with ſeuen huſbandes, ſo that ſhe became a reproche vnto her owne fathers maydes, laying to her charge that ſhe had ſtrangled her huſbandes. Thinke you (Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) your caſe is comparable to this? If it be ſo, then take that remedie which ſhe vſed, and miſtruſte not of the ſucceſſe that folowed, as you haue in the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Anna.</hi> So ſhe made her prayer to God the almightie, which is expreſſed in the hiſtorie, deſiring him to pitie her caſe, and by ſome meanes to take awaye her reproche: and accordingly the Lord (as his eares are alwayes open to the prayers that proceede from an humble ſpirit) gaue her to wife to good <hi>Tobias,</hi> with whom ſhe ſawe many a good day, and alſo for token of Gods bleſſing, iſſue of children. Euen ſo if we may hope for the beſt (and why ſhoulde you miſtruſt the matter,<note place="margin">Abraham.</note> ſeeing that <hi>Abraham</hi> in a more deſperate caſe, hoped againſt hope?)
<pb facs="tcp:7840:20"/>
the Lord our God I doubt not, pitieth your caſe ſo farre, that he will ſende you a truſtie <hi>Tobias,</hi> to whom you may betake your ſelfe without feare, with whom you may leade out your life in peace and comfortable quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by whom you may conceiue and beare ſome ſuch ſonne as is reported of <hi>Samuel,</hi> in whome you may reioyce as in an obedient ſonne, and in whom God may be glorified as his ſeruant. But if the example of <hi>Anna,</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi> do not ſo much moue you, if it be out of your hope to haue their good happe, let vs then returne againe to Chriſt our ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; righteous redeemer, at whoſe hand, when all other aydes do faile, we may be bold to fetche comfort, and that moſt plentifully.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Tobias</hi> come not,<note place="margin">An excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene the profite &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort that the wife may haue of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and the ſame we haue of our head and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Chriſt</note> yet you may wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelfe with Chriſt, finding that in him you ſhalbe ſped as fully as you can wiſh. You are of the flocke of the faithfull: then will he ſtande you to all purpoſes in ſtead of an huſband, not after an earthly, but after an heauenly ſort. Hee is the heade to defende and gouerne that bodye, whereof you are a member. Such as the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is to the wife, ſuch is Chriſt to thoſe that are of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Congregation, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. It is a great comfort in deede for
<pb facs="tcp:7840:21"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> to haue his <hi>Eue,</hi> and contrariwiſe: but Chriſt it is, that bleſſed ſeede, that hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them both. There is a narrow bond and copulation betwixt the wife &amp; her huſband, for they are reckoned one in fleſh: Euen ſo hath Chriſt, to make vs vnto him an holy ſpouſe, taken bone of our bones, and fleſhe of our fleſhe. Your huſband would cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you when your other friends would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake you, and Chriſt will accompanie and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt you when your huſband hath left you. He muſt ſometimes of neceſſitie be abſent from you, death ſhall make a grieuous diuorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt you: but no time may tye Chriſt from you: by him it is that you liue, &amp; that you liue well, he ſhall aſſiſt you at your dying day, and at the latter day he ſhall rayſe you againe. Your huſbande peraduenture, would thinke no money, no meate, no appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell to deare for you, and ſo doing, you would thinke him a good huſband: but whether he would die for you I doubt. But Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus that good ſhepheard hath ſhewed you ſo much loue, that he hath layd downe his life for you, he hath ſhed his bloud for you, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the death of the croſſe, he died for your ſinnes, and roſe againe for your iuſtification, and now maketh interceſſion for you, which
<pb facs="tcp:7840:21"/>
he will continue vntill the time he hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced you in his kingdome to reigne with him for euer.</p>
            <p>Thus (Siſter) as my ſimplicitie ſerueth me, I haue attempted that, which I feare I haue not obtained, (if it might be) to comfort you, or rather to tell you where you may ſeeke and finde comforte, then of my ſelf to make you any deede of gift: For God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the authour of al conſolation, therefore I referre you to him by your prayer, and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort vnto his worde, written for all our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes. I haue but ſomewhat aſſaied to playe <hi>Iohn Baptiſtes</hi> parte, I am not he of whom you muſt receiue this good gifte, but you muſt looke toward an other: Therefore I ſay vnto you of him whoſe ſhoolatchet I am not worthy to vnlooſe, Behold the Lambe of God who bringeth this comfort with him, a ſalue (me thinkes) ſufficient to heale all ſores, as that he is that Lambe that taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde. Nature hath ſo prouided that if we receiue any wound in the head, the whelke that is in the hande, the corne that is in the foote, we ſoone forget &amp; loſe the ſenſe thereof. O conſider (Siſter) howe your head was wounded, then ſhall your handes and your feete the leſſe grieue
<pb facs="tcp:7840:22"/>
you: Nowe againe our head is whole, triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing in heauen: why then ſhould our hearts be heauie on earth, as though the head had forgotten the bodie, or any part thereof? No (Siſter) doubte you not, he will not ſuffer an heare to periſhe of that bodie which he ſo dearely purchaſed, ſeeing that this mightie <hi>Michael</hi> hath ſubdued our archenemy,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.</note> that terrible dragon, and ſubtill ſerpent with his petie captaines, death and hell, what ſhould we be ſo much moued with any force of the fleſhe, or any miſchiefe that the worlde may worke vs? Yea, here alſo your Sauiour ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortably vnto you, ſaying, Be of good there, I haue ouercome the world. Seeing that he hath broken the head of our enemy, what ſhould his taile ſo much trouble vs? ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee hath taken away our ſinnes, what ſhould any ſorowes remaine amongſt vs? &amp; if we ſorowe not for our ſinnes, why doe we lament for any other earthly trifle? So (Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) if your eye be fully fixed on Chriſt your redeemer, ſeing his paines and his patience, you may not but quiet your ſelfe, conſidering his merites and his mercie, you can nothing miſtruſte but he that tooke away the greater burthen of your ſinnes, will alſo open you a waye out of your ſorowes, ſo that nowe you
<pb facs="tcp:7840:22"/>
haue no occaſion left of miſtruſt in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God. For he that gaue vs his Sonne,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> howe ſhould hee not with him giue vs all things alſo? and now your ioye muſt needes be full, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaieth. Say not then you are in miſerie, for you ſee preſent remedie ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing good aſſurance of eternall felicitie. And if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould aſke you how you proue your ſtate to be miſerable, I am ſure you can not proue ſo faſt as I can diſproue.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, I am an abiect in the world:<note place="margin">Comforts againſt the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the world, and ſorow and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines. 1. Cor. 12.</note> I anſwere, the more meeter for God, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker you are to your Sauiour: ſo ſaieth the Apoſtle to your comfort and mine, The vile thinges of the worlde, things deſpiſed and things of nought, hath God choſen.</p>
            <p>I am ſad and penſiue, (you will ſay) my meat doth mee no good, I enioye not the world. But theſe are no arguments, hereby to conclude miſeries. For euen the holy and happie <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſuch ſugar and ſauce to his meate, he mingled his bread with aſhes, and where was moſt likelyhood of reſt, his bed he watered with teares, ſo that of your ſorow it ſelfe you may receiue comfort, becauſe that ſhorte worldly ſorowes are but a paſſage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnſpeakeable, incredible, and eternall ioye and conſolation. Our Sauiour ſaith they are
<pb facs="tcp:7840:23"/>
happie that lament, for they ſhalbe comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but hee ſetteth a woe vpon thoſe that laughe: ſo that by his iudgement happines (and heauenly happines he ſpeaketh of) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth rather by lamenting then laughing. Yea,<note place="margin">Reue. 21.</note> God himſelf wil take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paines to wipe away the teares of the eyes of ſuch as ſheade any vnder the croſſe, &amp; eſpecially in the cauſe of his Chriſt. You haue litle comfort perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture in the worlde, yet I am ſure more then <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his penurie, or <hi>Iob</hi> in his perplexitie: and the leſſe you finde on earth, the more belike you ſhal haue in heauen. You knowe the anſwere to the riche man, in the parable, that he had his earthly pleaſure for his portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.25</note> But what an exchange made <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus?</hi> euen eternal pleaſure for temporal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie. If you haue not your portion with the riche man here; you may the leſſe doubte to haue parte and place with <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the kingdome of God. And here let Chriſt be your comforter: You ſhall lament (ſaith he) but the world ſhall reioyce, and in him, hee ſaith you ſhall haue peace. O ſee that pitifull and ſauing <hi>Samaritan,</hi> how he powreth wine and oyle into your woundes, euen the peace of conſcience, the peace of God that paſſeth all vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.18.</note> If the world hate you (ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:7840:23"/>
he) you know that it hated me before you: &amp; if our Sauiour hath lead vs the waye, what ſhould we ſticke at the matter? where as he hath ouerlept ſo great blockes, why ſhould we ſtumble ſo at euery ſtrawe which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill caſteth in our way? The Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.11, 12.</note> If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall raigne with him: and if we die with him, we ſhall liue with him. O Siſter, let vs not ſhrinke from our Captaine, whome we ſee already to be a conquerour. Let vs prepare our ſelues pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to abide the pleaſure of God: let vs exerciſe patience in the lighter, that we may the better beare the greater burden. Let vs liue and die with our Sauiour, let vs ſuffer with him in all patience, that we may reigne with him in glorie, to the which the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this world with all extremitie (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath caſt the matter) are nothing compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. We hope to haue our part in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt Ieſus, let vs not then looke for it there where he hath tolde vs it is not to be found: Let vs not ſeeke after worldly wealth or earthly felicitie, let vs not looke here to rule the roſte, but to be roſted rather of Rulers. Our kingdome is where Chriſt reigneth, let that content vs, knowing that his kingdome is aboue all powers, al things
<pb facs="tcp:7840:24"/>
being in ſubiection vnder his feete.</p>
            <p>Here I leaue you (Siſter) betaking you to Chriſt, who couereth you as one of his choſen chickens, vnder the ſhadow of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable winges, againſt whom as long as you liue, neither the world, which he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, neither death, which he hath ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp, neither the gates of hel, which he hath cloſed vnto you, ſhal any thing preuaile. That which I haue ſaid, I haue ſaid once, &amp; peraduenture as good vnſaid: but Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth you with his ſweete pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and euerlaſting word of ſaluation: he ſtill crieth vnto you, Be of good chere, I haue ouercome the worlde: reioyce in this (ſayth he) that your name is written in the booke of life. Betake you therefore wholy to him, reioyce in his croſſe, reſorte to his word, whence, as out of paradiſe you may gather flowers ſufficient to fill you with ioye. And if it hath pleaſed almightie God any thing to refreſhe you with this my poore poſy, his wil be done, his name be glorified, Amen: I haue my rewarde: and he the God of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion graunt vs the heauenly comfort of his holy Spirit, that peace which the world can not giue, and that conſtant patience in all his fatherly corrections, that we be not founde
<pb facs="tcp:7840:24"/>
falſe hirelings, but true and truſtie ſeruants: no baſtard children, but by vnfained faith, the bleſſed poſteritie of the bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and true regenerates of God by our Sauiour Chriſt. And the holie ſanctifying Spirit of trueth, and God be bleſſed for euer, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A verie godly and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Exhortation to ſuffer patiently impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, exile, or what miſerie ſoeuer els may happen to a man in this life for the profeſſion of the Goſpel of CHRIST IESVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the worlde hate you, good Brethren, and thereupon with ſundrie afflictions and griefes do moleſte and vexe you, marueile not with grudging, but prayſe GOD with patience, who in this fornace faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you to the lykeneſſe and image of his owne Sonne,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> whome the worlde hath ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the beginning, for whoſe ſake al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in no wiſe it can loue you, but with moſte ſpitefull hate will purſue you, euen vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:7840:25"/>
death, for that you are choſen by Chriſt from the worlde,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> to walke foorth and bring out fruite, which ſhall continue to ſanctification, whereof the end ſhalbe euerlaſting life. For as a riche and beautifull Harlot full of amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe filth, with a painted face, wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looks, trimme araye, fayre wordes, large promiſes, great giftes, &amp; with the entiſement of quiet, wealthie and pleaſant life, allureth them on whom ſhe caſteth loue (yet at the end rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them with pockes, piles, fighting, braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and moſt ſhamefull death) whom if ſhe can by no meanes entiſe to folow her fancie, ſhe hateth ſo deadly, that ſhe ceaſeth not, but cauſeth the whole rablement of her bawdie bawdes, ruffling royſterkins with brawling bragges, ſhamefull ſlaunders, ſubtill ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, quarreling queſtions, and falſly fayned accuſations, to vexe, trouble and bring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So the Princeſſe of the world, that moſt filthie harlot wooeth Gods children, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed vnto his ſonne Chriſt, to breake their faith and trouth to him plighted, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her dearlings, ſetting before their eyes all the kingdomes of the worlde and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thereof, promiſing with holowe holines, ſubtill ſuſpicion, falſely fained religion, and a pokefull of ſuch pretie perſuaſions, that if
<pb facs="tcp:7840:25"/>
they wil fal downe and worſhip as ſhe doeth, ſhe will giue vnto them all theſe ſame: for then ſhall they be her owne deare dearlings, and ſhe will loue them, as her owne: but the end ſhalbe moſt dreadful damnation.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> Whom if ſhe cannot perſwade, neither by one way or by other vnto her loue, from Chriſt their beſt and onely beloued ſpouſe, ſhe conceiueth ſo great an hatred againſt them, that ſhe ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all her champions with might &amp; maine to doe them diſpleaſure in their goods, to worke them hatred of their friendes, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre their good name, to puniſhe their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to offende their conſciences, to make their life yrkſome vnto them, and moſte cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly without mercie to kill them, yet whoſe death is moſt precious in Gods ſight, and hath to rewarde a moſt glorious reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus the worlde hath ſerued our deare and beſt beloued Chriſt before vs for our ſakes, who was giuen into the handes of this harlot to be thus cruelly dealt withall, for to be vnto vs a patern, which we ſhould folow,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> an image, after which we muſt be faſhioned, painted forth before our eyes in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to teache vs to folowe his trace with patience, and in running this race to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue comfort,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> hoping after victorie through fayth
<pb facs="tcp:7840:26"/>
in him,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> who both gaue vs warning of the paine, and leſt we ſhould faint, to comfort vs, promiſed victorie,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> ſaying, In the world ſhall you haue affliction, but in me peace: be of good cheare, for I haue ouercommed the worlde. To fight with a puiſſant enemie, whoſe courage was neuer abated, whoſe ſtrength is inuincible, and who hath bene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes aſſailed by many, but neuer vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, might diſcomfort a weake heart, and cauſe it to giue ouer at the firſt without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſiſtance: But for ſo much as this ſtern madame with all her chiualrie and force is ſo ouercome, and weakened to our handes, that ſhe is not able to reſiſt, what countenance ſo euer ſhe makes, much leſſe able to ouercome ſuch as doe ſtoutly withſtand her malice and crueltie, how faint hearted &amp; cowardly milk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoppes may we be iudged, that wil be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and may not abyde the lowring counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a feeble, maymed, and beaten brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, eſpecially ſeeing that in ſtriuing faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully againſt her and her ſouldiours, the loſſe of renowme here is the purchaſing of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glorie, the loſſe of worldly goods, the gayning of heauenly riches, the loſſe of a miſerable and ſhort life here, the winning and very entrance into a ioyfull and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb facs="tcp:7840:26"/>
life in heauen? Is the friendſhippe of the worlde ſo deare to vs, that therefore we ſhould not eſteeme Gods fauour? Ought our goods, wife, children, friendes, landes and poſſeſſions ſo much to be regarded, that for to ſaue them we ſhould forſake the heauenly riches and euerlaſting inheritance? Ought we to be ſo deſirous to liue here, that for a ſhort life and vnpleaſant, we will purchaſe an euerlaſting and moſt painefull death? But the burthen of pouertie is importable, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, impriſonment, exile is intolerable, the bitter ſtormes of perſecution, and the ſharpe ſhowres of death are ſo inſufferable, that we feare leaſt we ſhoulde not be of power to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide and paſſe thorow them, and therefore do thinke it better to ſit ſtill then to riſe &amp; take a fall, better not to enterpriſe the conflict, then in the middes for lacke of ſtrength through faintnes to giue ouer with ſhame, and runne away. How delicate, fearfull, and therefore vnwilling the fleſhe is to ſuffer, common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth, al men hauing any feeling of them ſelues perceiue, and chiefely they, who ſetting all perſuaſions of the fleſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, haue of full purpoſe and reſolute deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination with them ſelues, entred into the ſchoole of ſufferance, beginning at Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:7840:27"/>
his croſſe, and ſo forth to learne therein onely to glorie, can by that they feele in them ſelues beſt declare. For as the deadly foe to mankinde aſſaulted our deare brother Ieſus Chriſt then moſt hotly, after he perceiued by plaine tokens, that he was Gods Sonne, bent, by the croſſe and contempt of the world to enter into glorie with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firie dartes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> pouerty, ignominy, ſhame, &amp; afterward with the feare of death: on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other part, with plentie, riches, honour, poſſeſſions, and glorie of the whole world, knowing moſt perfectly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe perſwaſions ſhould be moſt ſtrong to moue &amp; perſuade the fleſhe to refuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, weying y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paines &amp; the trauail with one eye, &amp; the pleaſant wealthy honour with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other: ſo he ceaſſeth not to aſſayle Chriſtes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers with the ſelf ſame entiſements, to cauſe the fleſhe to abhorre the croſſe, and ſeeke after eaſe, but then moſt buſilie, when he percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the heart moued by Gods Spirit to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne theſe as vanities, and to ſeeke after true wealth, quietnes and glorie. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out al doubt the miſtruſt in Gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, wherewith all fleſhe is naturally infected, &amp; feare of the great painfull bitternes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, impriſonment, &amp; perſecution bringeth, alwayes obiected and propounded by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate
<pb facs="tcp:7840:27"/>
fleſhe, doth moue the heart of man to hate, and flye by alwayes the croſſe, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and pretende excuſes and cauſes which it ſhould be better to refuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enter into trouble, among which this is not the leaſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fleſh, not regarding Gods working in the middes of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, far aboue the capacitie of mans witte, pretendeth as though it would gladly for trueths ſake enterpriſe great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath not power giuen, able to go thorow withal accordingly. And this excuſe is prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded euen by them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet wil not ſeme to be fleſhly, but ſpirituall, not flattering the world for feare, but fauouring the trueth of loue, &amp; ſo deceiue them ſelues, where they vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake &amp; refuſe that thing they would ſeeme moſt gladly to obtayne. Wherein they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit double offence: of hypocriſie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would ſeeme to be that they are not: and of incredulitie, for that they declare plainely in this ſaying, that they thinke either that God can not, or els that he will not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and deliuer them forth of all miſeries, not eſteeming his promiſes, wherein he hath declared his will, neither marking his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous working for his children from time to time in their afflictions, wherein his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er moſt manifeſtly appeareth, neyther yet
<pb facs="tcp:7840:28"/>
conſidering his fatherlie care, which is more mindfull and tender ouer his, then the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can be ouer her onely beloued childe. It ſufficeth betwixt man and man, ſpecially if they be of honeſtie &amp; credit, that things paſſe by word and writing: we perſuade our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that the thing ſo promiſed &amp; confirmed ought and alſo ſhalbe performed. Vpon this perſuaſion, if the Prince promiſe to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, the noble man to the meane, the father to the ſonne, and among marchants one to another, it is accounted ſo ſure, that we will make our reckoning thereof, as though we had it in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſuch truſt we giue one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another: and ſhall we then doubt in Gods promiſe, which hath not only paſt by words, but alſo by writing ſealed, &amp; confirmed with the bloud and death of his onely Sonne? Is there any man ſo mindfull of his promiſe, or ſo able to performe the ſame, as our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Father is, of that he promiſeth to vs? It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſeene among men, that leagues, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenantes and bargaines can not be ſo wiſely made, nor ſo ſurely confirmed, but that with wyelie falſhoode and falſe vnfaithfulnes, they are defeated &amp; of none effect. But God is ſo faithful in performing the thing to vs, which he promiſeth, that heauen and earth ſhal ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:7840:28"/>
come to nothing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one title of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhalbe vnperformed. Yea, they that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt or doubt of the ſuretie of his promiſe, are no leſſe in doubt whether there be a God or no. For to doubt or denie his trueth and fidelitie, is to miſtruſt or denie him to be GOD. A Prince &amp; noble man for his owne honour ſake, a Father for his father like affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his childe, a Marchaunt for his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ſake will kepe their promiſe: &amp; would not our heauenly Prince (who as he hath made all things to ſerue to his owne glorie, ſo will not giue the ſame to any creature) haue his honour herein aduanced and moſt highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, that he is moſt ſure, iuſte, and true of promiſe? Would not our heauenly Father we ſhould perſuade our ſelues, that his loue towardes vs doth farre ſurmount the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a carnal father to his childe? Can any man ſo much eſteeme his owne credite, and eſtimation of truſtines, as he, who is faithful trueth it ſelfe, regardeth ſo to be knowen to his creatures? It is the greateſt diſhoneſtie among men to be ſo vnthankfull, to ſuſpect or miſtruſt him, whoſe friendlie fidelitie, and faithfull friendſhip we haue bene ſure of at al times, whenſoeuer we haue bene in diſtreſſe: much more ſhame is it, to ſuſpect, miſtruſt, or
<pb facs="tcp:7840:29"/>
doubt of Gods faythful aſſiſtance, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer we ſhal haue need, for ſo much as his faithful friendſhip, &amp; friendly loue is farre aboue the truſtines of man, as heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, fine golde aboue filthie droſſe, &amp; precious pearles aboue dirtie doung. Yea there is no engine, wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil worketh ſo forcibly mans deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which draweth ſo many fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, &amp; doth wring forth of Gods iuſtice his fearfull vengeance, as miſtruſt in gods promiſe, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity: On the other part, nothing attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſaluation, bringeth men nere to Gods preſence, &amp; draweth forth of gods mercie his fauourable loue, but only fayth &amp; conſtant af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance in his moſt ſure &amp; faithfull promiſes. The loſſe of riches, landes, &amp; earthly poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is a ſore grief: but is not the winning of an hundred fould ſo much, and the obtaining of an euerlaſting kingdome a good ſalue for this ſore? If we gaine with the loſſe of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie things, heauenly treaſures, with the forſaking of worldly frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, Chriſt to be our deare &amp; ſure friend, and with refuſing father, mother, brother, ſiſter, wife, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, purchaſe God to be our moſt mercifull Father, Chriſt our moſt louing brother, &amp; to be loued of the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, as his deare dearlings, &amp; only beloued ſpouſe, what haue wee loſt? what
<pb facs="tcp:7840:29"/>
greater gain can we haue? or what more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge can be made? This bargaine and profite hath our heauenly Father promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto vs by a byl of his owne hand, ſealed with the bloud of his only So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, teſtified by the witnes of his Apoſtles, and left with vs in our owne cuſtodie to be paide at the ſight, whenſoeuer we ſhall require it: whereof this is the content: Who ſo hath forſaken houſe,<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> brother, ſiſter, father, mother, wife, children, or landes for my Names ſake, he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue an hundreth folde, and the inheritance of euerlaſting life. Who will denie, but that hunger, colde, nakednes, extreme pouertie, &amp; want of things partly neceſſarie, are an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burden for man to beare? but the weight hereof is lightned and made eaſie to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that with right eye, &amp; vnfainedly,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> do beleue Gods promiſe, and caſt their care on him. Caſt thy care vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord, for he hath care ouer thee.<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> Your heauenly Father knoweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue neede of all theſe things, meate, drinke and clothes: he miniſtreth theſe things in due time to the beaſtes of the earth, the fouls of the aire, the fiſhes in the ſea, he clotheth and decketh with beautifull apparell the flowers of the fielde, according to his promiſe: and wil he not keepe his promiſe vnto vs, for whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:7840:30"/>
ſakes he hath made theſe creatures, and hath made vs lords ouer them?<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> What cauſe haue we rather to miſtruſt his promiſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birde that flieth forth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning vpon this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perſuaſion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe ſhal finde foode, not dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but he, who made her, wil not ſuffer her to ſterue with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger? Haue we ſeene ſuch as haue put their truſt in him, ſterue for hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, die of cold,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> periſh through nakednes? It hath not bin heard of, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the righteous hath bin for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> or his ſeede (begge) wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting bread. For they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> know the Name of the Lord, wil truſt therin: for he forſaketh not them, that ſeeke after him.<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> Seeke after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of God &amp; the righteouſnes therof, &amp; all theſe things ſhalbe miniſtred vnto you, ſaith Chriſt. If he be true that maketh this promiſe, why ſhould we feare hunger, colde, or nakednes? If he be not to be truſted, why will we take on vs his Name? If we cannot denie him, but to be moſt iuſt of promiſe, as he is in deede, we argue our ſelues of to much hypocriticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitie, when we ſaye, that we woulde gladly ſuffer theſe for his ſake, ſauing for feare to want neceſſaries in our neede, and that wee ſhall not be able to abyde it. And he hath promiſed no leſſe aſſiſtaunce, ayde, and comfort in all kinde of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:30"/>
whether it be impriſonment, baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, loſſe of life or any membre. Yea, becauſe we ſhould not faint in priſon, waxe feble in exile, giue ouer through feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bitter pangs &amp; ſharpe prickes of death, he hath promiſed not only to be reuenged on our perſecutors, but alſo to be preſent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, to helpe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> Wherfore he hath willed vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of our troubles to cal vpon him, adding this promiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil deliuer vs. Wherunto the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſo truſt, feling y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table trueth therof at ſundrie times in many and dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous perils, that he perſuaded him ſelf, al feare ſet apart, either of one painefull daunger or other whatſoeuer: yea, if it were to walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valley of the ſhadow of death, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould not haue cauſe to feare, comforting him ſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſaying, which was Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made vnto vs al, For thou art with me:<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> Thy rod &amp; thy ſtaffe, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort me. Is Gods ſtaffe waxed ſo weake, that we dare not leane to much now theron, leſt it ſhould breake? Or is he now ſuch a cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geling, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil not be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in our troubles according to his promiſe? Wil he not giue vs his ſtaffe to ſtay vs by, and reache vs his hande to holde vs vp, as he hath bene wonte to doe? If he be the ſelfe ſame God and no chaunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:31"/>
when we be put into priſon, or led into captiuitie, he goeth with vs, or throwen into the ſea to be drowned, he doeth not leaue vs, or caſt into the raging fyre, he is with vs, to this ende, either to deliuer vs from the violent force of them vtterlie, or at the leaſt ſo to comfort vs in the middes of them, that we ſhould rather take pleaſure therein, then feele payne. Wherefore he cryeth vnto vs continually:<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> Feare not thou litle flocke: feare not them, that can doe no more but kil the body, that is their vttermoſt: but now the Lord that made thee (O <hi>Iacob</hi>) and he that faſhioned thee (O <hi>Iſrael</hi>) ſaith thus,<note place="margin">Eſa. 43.</note> Feare not, for I will defende thee, I wil call thee by thy name, thou art myne: when thou wenteſt in the waters, I was by thee, that the ſtrong floudes ſhould not plucke thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, when thou walkeſt in the fier, it ſhal not burne thee, and the flame ſhal not kindle vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee: For I am the Lord thy God, the holy one of Iſrael, thy ſauiour. Let the cruel Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes rage and roare, let the obſtinate <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> fret and fume, let the rableme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtes ſouldiours, the deuils owne deare dearlings threaten with ſacke, ſworde, fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got and fire, yet if God be with vs, who can be againſt vs? the mightie, ſtrong, holy one
<pb facs="tcp:7840:31"/>
of Iſrael hath made a faithfull promiſe, that he wil be with vs, defend &amp; deliuer vs.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> This promiſe ſufficeth to a Chriſtian to arme him againſt all feare of trouble, anguiſhe, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, hunger, nakednes, perill, ſworde and death, for that none of al theſe can ſeparate vs from God, but we ſhall ouercome, and haue the ouerhand in all theſe things through the aide and comfort of him, who hath loued vs: for he is a faithfull God, which wil not ſuffer vs to be tempted aboue our ſtrength, but ſhal in the middes of temptation make a way to come out, that we may beare it. Who nowe weying theſe promiſes dare ſurmiſe that God will not ayde, comfort, and ſtrengthen you in all neceſſities? And will you thinke he is not able to performe the thing he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth? Is the arme of the Lorde ſhortened? Shall not he who is able to raiſe of ſtones children vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> be of power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, relieue &amp; defend, whom he hath already made? If we be aſſured of his wil, which his promiſe teacheth vs, we neede not doubt of his power: for whatſoeuer him pleaſeth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.5.</note> he doeth in heauen, earth, the ſea, and in al deepe places. If we beleue his promiſe,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> all things are poſſible, yea there is nothing, but it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy of him to be done. As a mighty Captaine,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:32"/>
who hath vnder his gouernment many ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers &amp; ſeruants, hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when he biddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go, they go, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith abide, they abide, &amp; when he willeth them to do this or that, they obey his word: ſo is paine, pleaſure, grief, eaſe, ſicknes, health, life, death at the becke &amp; cal of God, that they come &amp; go at his appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as the faithful Centurion confeſſeth in the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Matth. 8.</note> Yea he worketh ſo forcibly in his children, that leane wholy vnto his promiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maketh to them of paine, a pleaſure, of grief, an eaſe, of ſicknes health, &amp; of death, life: as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuing, pleaſure, eaſe, health, life is a weary irkſome, &amp; painful death. When you were in proſperitie, had the true religion of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you, &amp; were ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g within your ſelues, as no foreine Prince could inuade and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you, the Lord of hoſts turned al vpſide down in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twinkling of an eie, hath wrapt you vp in aduerſity, choked your whole realme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> falſe ſuperſtition, &amp; giuen you vp into the rule and gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch leane locuſts, ſtinging ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; ſpiteful ſpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, as no people haue bene heretofore plagued withall. And is the Lords power not ſo able to deliuer his from theſe miſeries, to reſtore his true religion, and vanquiſhe theſe <hi>Sodomitical Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7840:32"/>
as it was to giue them vp, for a time to be chaſtened, into their ſubiection? Let the Idolatrous Papiſtes aſcribe their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and whole felicitie vnto their Idols and God of bread: yet our hope is in the Lord, who hath made heauen and earth, who can, and wil for his owne glories ſake, ſhewe him ſelfe to be the onely God of might in giuing ouerthrowe to theſe Idolatours with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine confuſion, when they thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues moſt ſure, and looke leaſt for it. Let them nowe for a while fret and fume againſt the Lord and his Chriſt, ſhake of his yoke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> and breake his bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in ſunder: Yet is the Lord in his holie temple, his abiding is in heauen, his eyes beholde theſe ſonnes of men, and laugh them to ſcorne, and at the length ſhal talke with them in his furie, powring vpon them from heauen, ſnares, fyre, and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, whoſe cup and portion ſhalbe burning ſtorme and tempeſt. Let them perſuade them ſelues, and beleeue darkenes to be light, trueth falſnes, blindnes ſight, and life death, and bring this to paſſe, that mens eyes may ſeeme with a ſkinne or ſlime of ſuperſtitious ignorancie to bee couered and made blinde, yet can the Lord, and alſo will, when he ſeeth time, reſtore light, trueth, ſight &amp; life againe
<pb facs="tcp:7840:33"/>
to the aduancement of his owne glorie, the comfort of his Church, and vtter confuſion of his enemies.<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> Folowe therefore after the Lord, crye vnto him with the two blind men, deſire him of his mercy to reſtore your ſight, miſtruſt not but he is able to doe it, ſaye with them that you ſo beleeue, and the Lord wil make you anſwere and performe it in dede: after your faith be it vnto you. If you truſte in the Lord and confeſſe him to be om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotente, why ſhould you feare the crueltie of Antichriſt, who afflicteth Chriſt in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, perſecuting and puniſhing their ſoules with ſuperſtition, idolatrie and vnbeliefe, and afflicting their bodies with hunger, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, exile and painful death? Hath not God aforetime aſſiſted his to wade thorowe, and ouercome the paines of all theſe, yea in the middes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bitter ſtormes to take great pleaſure? And is he of leſſe power to helpe vs? ſhall not we now by his aſſiſtance be ſo able to abide, and take pleaſure in paines, as our brethren haue bene before vs? My bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> be ſtrong in the Lord, and through the power of his ſtrength learne, to whatſoeuer eſtate God ſhal call you, therewith to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,<note place="margin">Philip. 4.</note> knowing how to be lowe, &amp; how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, euery where and in al thinges inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:7840:33"/>
both to be full and to be hungrie, both to haue plentie, and to ſuffer neede, yea, to do all things through Chriſt, who ſtrengtheneth you, by whom alſo you ſhal ouercome. For if you be troubled on euery ſide,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> yet ſhall you not be without ſhift: when you bee vexed with pouertie, you ſhall not be vtterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſomewhat: wrapt in perſecution, not forſaken therein: caſt downe, yet periſhe not: that the excellencie of the power may bee Gods, and that you may onely glorie in the Croſſe of Chriſt. By the croſſe he entred into glorie, and they that are his, muſt enter in the ſame way. The Princes had no power ouer him, further then was giuen them from aboue, neither haue they ouer you,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> no not to plucke of one heare of your head, for they be all numbred, and not one falleth away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the will of your heauenly Father,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> who worketh all things for the beſt to all them that loue him. And woulde we not haue all things worke to our moſt aduantage? In worldly things we ſeeke after moſt gaine, and wil we neglect that in heauenly things? For to winne a ſmall ſumme of money, we will take vpon vs a farre iourney in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of robbing, in perils of drowning, and let for no payne, perſwading our ſelues that
<pb facs="tcp:7840:34"/>
God wil be with vs, aſſiſt and proſper vs in all our trauayle: and ſhall wee refuſe to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile by land, to paſſe the ſeas, to ſuffer what paine ſoeuer thereunto belongeth, to winne the penny of euerlaſting life, miſtruſting that God will not be with vs, ayde and further vs in whatſoeuer painefull perill we ſhall come in? O blinde incredulitie, that makeſt eaſy things to ſeeme hard by working an vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes in the mindes of men, whome thou ruleſt! If men forſake their own willes, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them ſelues wholy vnto Gods will, what thing can bee to harde? But if we will followe the appetites and delicate niceneſſe of our owne willes, what can be eaſy? Crye therefore with Chriſt, (deare brethren,) Not our wylles, but thy will (O heauenly Father) be done: So eſchue troubles, as may ſtande with his good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: When they come vpon you, embrace them willingly, ſuffer them patiently, wade thorowe them faithfully, for that is his good will and pleaſure. Folowe the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſte, of the Prophetes, Apoſtles, and holy martyrs, who were not wedded to their owne willes, but ſubmitted them ſelues wholy vnto Gods will, who wrought ſo with them, that in pouertie they wanted not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:34"/>
in priſon among rauening Lions they liued harmeles, in the middes of fyre they burnt not, in the moſt cruell torments they felt no payne, and truſting to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promiſe and mightie ayde of their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, deſired rather to be exerciſed vnder the croſſe, to die with Chriſt, then to be at eaſe, and liue with the world.<note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> with his Father <hi>Thare</hi> forſooke his natiue countrey,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.</note> and from thence was commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to depart into a countrey, whereof he neither knewe the name, where it was, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities were therein for men to liue withall, neither yet could he abide there any whyle: for a great dearth did op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the whole land, ſo that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to flye into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where he was in daunger of much diſpleaſure, for he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued before he entred, that he muſt forgoe either his wyfe, or els ſuſtaine daunger for keeping her. Hee was conſtrained often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to remoue his habitation not without great loſſe, trauayle and perill.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> alſo went forth of his natiue countrey into a ſtraunge place, partlie for that his father would not that hee ſhould be ioyned in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, with the daughters of the Idolatours of that countrey, partly to flye the crueltie of
<pb facs="tcp:7840:35"/>
wicked <hi>Eſau</hi> his naturall brother, where he ſerued <hi>Laban</hi> fourteene yeres for his two daughters,<note place="margin">Gen. 46.</note> in keeping his ſheepe: a paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full kinde of labour. Afterwarde in his olde daies was conſtrained by the force of a great dearth to remoue into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring was grieuouſly moleſted many yeres. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was ſolde by his brethren to the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelites,</hi> and by them vnto an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> where he ſuſteined great paine and perill in a ſtraunge countrey.<note place="margin">3. Reg. 19.</note> The Prophete <hi>Ely,</hi> being perſecuted by the wicked <hi>Iezabel,</hi> fled from poſt to pillar.<note place="margin">Dan. 1.</note> The Prophete <hi>Daniel</hi> with a great number of good and godlie Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites were caried into <hi>Babylon</hi> captiues, there to liue in captiuitie in a ſtraunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey among their deadly enemies. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Chriſt, and many godly men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo women in their time forſooke all they had, and went into ſtraunge cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels ſake. And after their time to this our time the Eccleſiaſtical hiſtories are full of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> examples both of men and alſo women, that left landes and goodes, fled their countreis, and did chooſe rather in an vnkoth and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> land to liue in hardnes with freedom of conſcience, to ſerue God after his wil, then to tarie at home in wealth with bondage of
<pb facs="tcp:7840:35"/>
conſcience, and diſhonour the Lord in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying his holy will. It is not read that any of theſe did murmure &amp; grudge to leaue their houſes, landes, goodes, and natiue countreis, fearing the want of friendſhip, the hatred of ſtraungers, the burden of pouertie, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of hunger, and the lack of things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for mans life here, nor yet that they came into any ſuch diſtreſſe, but that they had ſufficiencie, if not of the fineſt ſort, yet ſuch as ſerued their turne, and they wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. <hi>Abraham</hi> when he perceiued it ſtode with the Lordes will he ſhould departe, he wiſt not whither, nor what ſhift to make, did not debate the matter with himſelfe, take counſail of his friendes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult with his wife, whether he ſhould do the thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God or no, but ſetting apart all perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and wiſedome of fleſh, bowed downe his owne will ſubiect vnto Gods pleaſure, bent himſelfe without further delaye to obey his will, that ought onely to be obeyed in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of creatures: and therefore in a ſtraunge countrey, yea in the middes of his enemies, had not onely at all times ſufficiencie, but alſo did growe vnto great aboundance of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Of like ſort <hi>Iacob</hi> was not onely not left deſtitute of ſuccour, but did come to ſo
<pb facs="tcp:7840:36"/>
great aboundance, that at his returne into his countrey, hee made therewith his moſt mortall foe, his deare friende, and ſerued the Lord all his life in great wealth. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beeing a bondman in a ſtraunge countrey, was not ſo moued with the feare of falſe and ſlaunderous accuſations, of hunger, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonement, and ſuch like griefes, that hee would, to eſchue theſe, committe vncleane things againſt Gods will, but cleauing to Gods prouidence, was foſtered vp againſt the rage of hunger, the violence of impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, cleanſed from the fowle ſpottes of ſlaunders, ſet at libertie, and at length made ruler ouer <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Although his brethren meant his deſtruction, when they ſolde him to ſtraungers,<note place="margin">Gen. 45.</note> and droue him forth of his natiue countrey, yet he acknowledgeth this their fact to be the good will of GOD, who worketh all thinges to the beſt for them that loue him, whether it be hunger, colde, exile, impriſonment, or death it ſelfe, and maketh that which ſeemeth painefull and grieuous, eaſye and pleaſaunt. What ſhould wee ſaye to the Prophets <hi>Ely</hi> and <hi>Daniel? Ely</hi> flying the fiercenes of <hi>Achab,</hi> becauſe he ſhould not ſuffer more payne of hunger, then he might well awaye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:36"/>
was fedde by rauens ſent vnto him morning and euening,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 17.</note> to bring him bread and meate for that purpoſe, and afterwarde by a poore wydowe of <hi>Sarephta,</hi> and laſt of all by Gods Angell,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 19.</note> when hee was in a deſert, flying the crueltie of <hi>Iezabel.</hi> In like ſort <hi>Daniel</hi> was fedde in the pryſon by <hi>Habacuc</hi> brought by Gods Angell,<note place="margin">Dan. 14.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayde: O Lord thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred me, thou doeſt not forſake them that loue thee. A ſaying of hym, who had felt the eaſe and reliefe, that GOD pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth for all them that vnfainedly truſt in him, worthy to be written in golden letters, and deepely grauen into our heartes. This is a common and pleaſant perſuaſion to the Apoſtles, and al other of Chriſtes Churche, who ſuffered for Chriſtes ſake, pouertie, exile, perſecution, that in the middes of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie they were moſt riche, when they had nothing left them at all, then had they all thinges, and wanted nothing. Theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſhoulde moue vs to ſet apart all feare of want, and to caſt our care whollye vpon the Lorde, for ſo much as hee is no leſſe our louing and mercifull Father, then hee was to <hi>Abraham</hi> or any other: yea, he hath exhibited vnto vs in deede, and wee
<pb facs="tcp:7840:37"/>
haue ſeene that <hi>Abraham</hi> woulde gladlye haue beholded.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> God hath not ſpared his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne, but hath giuen him for vs all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death: howe much more will he giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, if we truſt in him, all other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie thinges? It is not a neceſſarie thing to haue ſtrength and ablenes to abide pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently for his ſake, not onely pouertie, loſſe of goodes, impriſonment and exile, but alſo power to paſſe thorowe eaſely the burning flames of fyre, hanging, drawing, ſtoning, racking, deuouring with wilde beaſtes, broy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, boyling, and ſuch kinde of moſt cruell tormentes and bitter death, as the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Chriſt, the olde tyrantes and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt him ſelfe, the Pope with his clergie now daily inuenteth and practiſeth to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe and fraye men from Chriſt? God hath alwayes to his tyme giuen his ſuch ſtrength to ouercome and contemne theſe, and whatſoeuer crueltie coulde be inuented, yea he hath ſo encouraged them to take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the middes of moſt crueltie, that they reioyced moſt, when they ſemed to be in the greateſt payne, as it is playne in manie hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of the Churche: and will not God deale ſo mercifully with vs nowe, as with them of olde time? Is his mercie waxed
<pb facs="tcp:7840:37"/>
leſſe nowe towardes vs, or his power not ſo able? God is not like vnto man to chaunge his purpoſe, and to be euery yere of a newe minde, he is faythfull, he chaungeth not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to the iudgement of the fleſhe he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to forſake the man that is caſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, baniſhed his countrey, throwen into the fire, and moſt cruelly dealt withall, yet he is preſent with him, aydeth and comforteth much more ſtrongly, then the tormentours be able to grieue or diſcomfort, yea, turneth the bitterneſſe into ſweeteneſſe, the payne into pleaſure, and that, which ſeemeth vnto others moſt vntolerable, to be moſt ſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The three Iſraelites were commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to fall downe and worſhippe the golden Image, they did not diſſemble the matter,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> but playnely ſaide they woulde not: they were threatened to be caſt into the burning fornace, they feared it not, they might haue diſſembled the matter for a time, following the world, but they knew GOD could not be deceiued, nor woulde not be plaied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. The ouen was made ſeuen times hotter, then euer before, &amp; they caſt into it, yet were they well able to abyde it, and had much more ſolace in the burninge fyre, then they that onely looked on. The mother with her
<pb facs="tcp:7840:38"/>
ſeuen ſonnes in the <hi>Machabees</hi> choſe rather to ſuffer moſt cruell death,<note place="margin">2. Mach. 7. 1. Mach. 2. 2. Mach. 6.</note> which they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thorowe moſt ioyfully, then to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte the leaſt thing againſt the Lawe of their GOD.<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. hiſt. lib. 6. cap. 4.</note> So likewyſe <hi>Mathathias</hi> his ſonnes, and <hi>Eleazarus. Rhais</hi> that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian woman, although not yet ſo fully ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized, that ſhee was admitted to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, ſet on fyre with the burning heate of Gods Spirit, and the famous chaſte wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Potamiena</hi> with her mother <hi>Marcella,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. hiſt. lib. 6. cap. 5.</note> after they had ſuffered great and horrible tormentes for the truthes ſake, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in burning fyre.<note place="margin">Eccle. hiſt. li. 6. cap. 41</note> 
               <hi>Quinta</hi> the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman and conſtant martyr of Chriſt, ſuffered rather to haue her legges tied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to bee drawen thorowe the ſtreetes vpon the ſharpe ſtones, and whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped moſt ſharpelie, then ſhe would ſeeme to worſhippe the images or idoles in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. The conſtant olde matrone <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> was beaten about the lace till all her teeth were beaten out, a great heape of woode ſet on fyre before her face, and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened to be caſt thereinto quicke, if ſhe would not agree to the Idolatours, and did willin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly chooſe to be burnt in the raging fyre. So likewiſe the hiſtorie ſheweth of <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narion,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:38"/>
Mercuria, Dionyſia,</hi> and other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table women, that were ſo vnfearefull to ſuffer moſt ſharpe death, that they woulde runne, when they heard, where the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in hande, and carie their young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with them (ſuch delight had they to ſuffer for Chriſtes ſake) in great haſt as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ioyfull feaſt, fearing nothing els, but that the tormentours would ſpare them, and that they ſhould not be thought worthie to beare witneſſe to Chriſtes death with their owne bloud. Call to your remembrance that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman and worthie martyr of Ieſus Chriſt your owne countrie woman <hi>Anne Askew:</hi> her impriſonment moued her not, ſhe litle weyed the cruel torture and tearing her bodie on the racke, ſhe ioyfully went to the fyer, and was of more comfort in feeling the paine, and leſſe wearie thereof, then the lookers on to beholde, or the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours to do execution. The hiſtorie ſayeth, that <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> a yong man, was ſo grieuouſly torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with diuers and ſundrie kindes of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and at length his bodie ſo rent and torne, that they left him for dead: Whome <hi>Ruffinus</hi> the writer of the Eccleſiaſticall ſtorie, afterward aſked whether he felt not grieuous paines, whiles he was in the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:39"/>
to whom he aunſwered, that he felt verie litle paine: For, ſaid he, there ſtood, as he thought, a yong man by him, who always wiped the ſweat from him, and ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted his ſtomacke, that the time of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting ſeemed to him much more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt then painefull. Who made the yong men walke in the fire and burne not? Who hardened theſe martyrs of men and women, that they did not ſhrinke at paine, but ranne thorow fire, water, and moſt cruell torments, and not be ouercome? Certainely euen he, who had promiſed them, that neither in fier, water, no nor yet in the ſhadowe of death he woulde be from them, but woulde be their buckler, defendour and ſhield, faithfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that no temptation ſhould ſo aſſaile them, but that he woulde giue a ioyfull ende and deliuerance: whereunto they truſted, and ſo by their conſtant fayth ouercame, and had the victorie. For this is the victorie that ouercommeth the worlde,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.</note> euen our fayth. Yea as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time woulde not ſerue vs, if we would rehearſe how the Patriarks, prophets, Apoſtles &amp; Martyrs through faith ſubdued kingdomes, wrought righteouſnes, obtained the promiſes, ſtopped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthes of Lyons, quenched y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> violence of fire, eſcaped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7840:39"/>
edge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſworde, out of weaknes were made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the armies of the aliants, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> women receiued their dead rayſed to life againe. Other were racked and would not be deliuered, that they might inherit a better reſurrection. Againe, other were tried with mockings and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, moreouer with bonds and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were ſtoned, were hewen in ſunder, were tempted, were ſlaine with ſworde. And theſe al through fayth obtayned good report. The holy Ghoſt hath cauſed theſe hiſtories to be kept in writing for vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are now in the latter dayes, to this ende, that we ſhould not onely behold in them the fierie raging of the world from the beginning againſt the choſen people of God, &amp; how ſtoutly they withſtood &amp; ouercame by faythfull patience the malice therof, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by reading of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ſhould in our like troubles, learne like patience, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, &amp; being thorowly tried, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue a ſure hope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame victorie, which they after many &amp; ſundrie trials did winne: whereof we ſhal not be diſapointed, if we to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende ſtriue lawfully. If it be to hard &amp; aboue your capacitie to beholde al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtories &amp; exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples propounded in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, &amp; the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of Chriſtes church with ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:40"/>
that you may eſpie &amp; behold in them the order of Gods working with his Church in all ages, wherby to perceiue theſe your grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous chaunges to be no new and vnwonted work of God: If you doe not perceiue &amp; ſee in them the true &amp; iuſt cauſe, which moueth the Lord hereunto, and thereby to learne faithful repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance: &amp; if you doe not vnderſtand in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent peruſing them, that the end and iſſue was alwayes ioyfull and glorious victorie &amp; deliueraunce, wherewith to comfort your ſelues in the middes of miſeries, take into your handes the comfortable hiſtorie of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> marke his whole life from that time he was taken from his fathers ſheepe to his death: beholde in him, your ſelues: in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple during the time of his rule, the church of England: and in the wonderfull iudgement of God in ordering his Church then, what ſhalbe the ende of his ſharpe croſſe, wherwith he doeth exerciſe you at this time. And to the ende you may the better ſee, how to wade in conſidering his whole life, we haue diſcloſed and opened for you to beholde a part thereof: wherein you ſhall ſee plainely, that the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous afflictions of euery one of you ſeueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of the whole Church of England to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, is not fallen by chaunce of euill or
<pb facs="tcp:7840:40"/>
good fortune, but by the mightie hande of God, whoſe good will it is thus to haue you tried for a while, alſo for what cauſe GOD thus worketh, and what ſhalbe the ende of al theſe dooings. After the Lorde had founde out <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man after his owne minde, and appointed him King ouer his people, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured worthily to deliuer and defend Gods people from their enemies the Idolatours, that dwelt nere about them, he did not grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to him ſuch quietnes, neither to his people, but that he was in continuall troubles, and no ſmall daungers, during the life of <hi>Saul,</hi> and alſo after his death, the Idolatours, and alſo <hi>Sauls</hi> friends, ſeeking all the wayes that might be, to diſturbe him forth of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And not onely was he thus vexed with his foraine enemies, but alſo moſt grieuouſly of all, by thoſe of his houſhold, who ſhoulde haue bin his moſt deare friends, his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſonne <hi>Abſalom,</hi> his moſt priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelours, the nobilitie of his Realme, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of his ſubiectes.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Abſalom</hi> pretending to his father <hi>Dauid</hi> a great holines, (as the maner of the hypocrites is) deſired to haue leaue to go into <hi>Hebron,</hi> there to doe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the performance of a vowe, which he had made in the time of his being in <hi>Syria,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7840:41"/>
but his meaning was to obtaine the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from his Father, and to ſtirre all <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt him, which he brought to paſſe: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was baniſhed, and purſued vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death by his owne ſonne, who wrought ſo much vilanie againſt his father, that he did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare in the deſpite of him, to miſuſe his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wiues in the ſight of all the people: how grieuouſe and daungerous this ſodaine chaunge was to <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; to the godly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which were but a very fewe in reſpect of the great number of the malicious hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, which folowed <hi>Abſalom,</hi> it appeareth plainly in the ſtorie, and you may eaſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. The beſt that was like to come of the matter, was, that whiles the kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was thus deuided, Gods enemies the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> who had lyen long in wayte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhoulde ſnatche vp from both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the kingdome of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not onely vtterly baniſhe Gods true religion from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but alſo bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their countrey, and their poſteritie into moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bondage and thraldome, and that, to Gods enemies the moſt vile people, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all the world. <hi>Dauid</hi> in all theſe peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous daungers of his owne lyfe, loſſe of his kingdome, &amp; vtter deſtruction of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:41"/>
did not diſcourage himſelf, but vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this to be the worke of Gods owne hande, acknowledging the true cauſe vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, did perſwade him ſelf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord after a time, when his good wil ſhould be, woulde giue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable end to al theſe ſtormes and bitter pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. His whole behauiour he himſelf deſcribeth in a Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 3.</note> which is left in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for vs to learne therafter how to behaue our ſelues in the like perſecutions. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was fled from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; the prieſtes were departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him with the Arke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords Couenaunt,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 15.</note> he went vpon mount Oliuet barefoote, wept as he went, and had his head couered, and ſo did all the people that were with him. And he made his mone vnto the Lord, ſaying, O <hi>Iehoua,</hi> how are they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed that trouble me?<note place="margin">Pſalm. 3.</note> how many are they that riſe againſt me, howe many are there that ſaye of my ſoule, There is no helpe for him in his God? <hi>Selah.</hi> Wonder not though this good King with an heauie hearte, and ſorowfull cheare doeth lament and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile his dolorouſe eſtate. Woulde it not grieue a King, when he thinketh of no ſuch matter, ſodainly to be caſt out of his Royall ſeate, and brought in daunger of his lyfe, and that by his owne naturall Sonne?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7840:42"/>Can the diſpleaſure of any enemie ſo much pearce the heart of a kinde father, as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall crueltie of the ſonne to ſeeke his death, of whom he himſelfe had his life? It grieued him no ſmall deale to perceiue ſuch as had bin his wiſe Counſailours, whom he much truſted, (whoſe duetie it had bin, with the ſpending of their owne liues, to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the common weale brought to good and quiet order, both in matters of policie, &amp; of Gods true religion,) to be the ſupporters and mainteiners of an hypocrite, who had neither reſpect to Gods true honour, nor yet conſideration of duetie to his moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Father, neither yet regarde to the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous weale of his natiue countrey. But nothing of all theſe grieued him ſo much, as this one thing, the remembrance and true acknowledging in himſelfe, that he himſelfe was the only cauſe of all theſe euils. He cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to his remembrance, that theſe plagues fell vpon him ſent from God, whoſe worke it was, and that for his ſinnes, which were the cauſe thereof, and this made him weepe and mourne. For ſo ſoone as the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> had warned him of his offence,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 12.</note> he cryed, <hi>peccaui,</hi> I haue ſinned: and afterward when hee ſawe this grieuous and ſodaine
<pb facs="tcp:7840:42"/>
chaunge folowe, he perceiued it came partly for his ſinne by the worke of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſubmitted him ſelf wholy to Gods will, ſaying,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 15.</note> If I ſhall finde fauour in the eyes of the Lorde, he will bring me againe, and ſhew me both his Arke and the Tabernacle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but, and the Lorde thus ſaye, I haue no luſt vnto thee, behold here am I, let him doe with mee what ſeemeth good in his eyes. Thus the worthie man of God acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his troubles to be of Gods hande, his ſinnes to be the cauſe, and therefore humbly and faithfully ſubmitteth himſelfe to Gods ordering, wel content to receiue whatſoeuer ſhould be layd vpon him. He aſſured himſelfe that when he himſelfe were moſt weakeſt, then God would declare his ſtrength for his owne glories ſake, and after he were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a faithfull repentaunce by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of his mercifull Father, then the rod ſhould be caſt into the fire. This conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of plagues both to priuate men particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and alſo of Realmes &amp; whole common Wealthes is diligently to be weyed, that as they come from God, ſo haue they this ende, that they tende partly to his owne glorie, partly to our profit, and amendement. For although ſinne is the generall cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:7840:43"/>
all mankinde generally was, is, &amp; ſhalbe moleſted with many and ſundrie kindes of troubles and calamities, yet the calamities &amp; afflictions are not to all kinde of men alike, nor yet for one end and purpoſe. For the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and reprobate are puniſhed &amp; whipped of God to a farre other end and meaning, then the godly and choſen children, who are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true church of God, the liuely me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt, &amp; ſuch as ſhalbe neuer ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God and his louing fauour in Chriſt Ieſu. Theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be neuer without trouble in this world, but alwayes exerciſed vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, yet the cauſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration why God will haue them thus exerciſed, is either for the glorie and honour of his owne Name, or the profite, commoditie; and exceeding benefit of them whom he thus afflicteth, either els for both theſe conſiderations together, for that there is no trouble that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to Chriſtes church or any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber therof, which appeareth not plainly to redound to Gods glorie, &amp; the profit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflicted, if it be wel &amp; iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Theſe two cauſes &amp; conſiderations doth the Scripture teach in all calamities of the church, whether they be generall or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which being wel marked, will eaſily put out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way this ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling block, wherat ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:7840:43"/>
ſtumble &amp; fal, marueyling wherfore God wil ſuffer his word, &amp; his choſen childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus to be vſed &amp; euil dealt withall. The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael were in Egypt moſt cruelly dealt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al 400. yeeres, oppreſſed with moſt painfull labours, moſt ſeruile exactions, their infants ſlaine, they cried vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, their griefs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, for God had hardened <hi>Pharao</hi> his heart, that he ſhoulde not eaſe or deliuer his people. Wherefore did God thus afflict his people, and ſtirred this cruell tyrant ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly to vexe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? truely for his own glorie, &amp; their profit. God rehearſeth this cauſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, of the hard &amp; cruel hearts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Egyptians</hi> towards his people, The <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſhal know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am the Lord,<note place="margin">Exod. 7.</note> and that I will deliuer my people by ſtrong hand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Exod. 9.</note> For this purpoſe (ſaith God to <hi>Pharao</hi>) haue I rayſed thee vp, that in thee I may declare my power thorowout the whole world. This profit they receiued, the exerciſe of their faith, the triall of their patience, and the confirming of their hope for deliueraunce, which was not deceyued. Thus <hi>S. Paul</hi> noteth and collecteth of this hiſtorie, the one end to be Gods glorie,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> for the honourable fame and renowme of his Name throughout the whole world, and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:7840:44"/>
the profit that the afflicted receiue, which is the exerciſe of faith,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> as he noteth of <hi>Moſes</hi> and his parents to the <hi>Hebrues.</hi> But much more plainly doth <hi>S. Paul</hi> note &amp; teach theſe two conſiderations to the Corinthes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> But we haue this treaſure in earthen veſſels, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power which excelleth, might be of God, and not of vs. We are troubled on euery ſide, yet are we not without ſhift: we are in pouertie, but not vtterly without ſomewhat: we are perſecuted, but we are not forſaken: we are oppreſſed, neuertheleſſe we periſhe not. But ſeeing we haue the ſame Spirit of faith (according as it is writteng beleeued, and therefore haue I ſpoken) we alſo beleeue, and therefore we ſpeake. For we knowe that he which rayſed vp the Lord Ieſus, ſhall raiſe vs vp alſo by the meanes of Ieſus. Therefore we are not wearie, but though our outwarde man be corrupt, yet the inwarde man is renued day by day. For our trouble, which is but temporall and light, worketh an exceeding and an eternall weight of glorie vnto vs. What can <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſpeake more to the commendation of Gods prayſe and glorie, then that the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his mightie power is declared and aduaunced in this, that his are troubled, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:44"/>
perſecuted, oppreſſed, and yet in all theſe doe not periſhe nor faint, but ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by him, who hath willed his in all their troubles to call vpon him, and he will ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them, that his Name ſhall thereby be glorified, and honoured? And what greater profit can come to the Church, then to haue the faith of Gods children ſo exerciſed, that the inward man may be renued day by day, and that as Chriſt entred into his glorie by troubles, the croſſe, and death, ſo alſo our troubles, which are but ſhort and light in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his, may worke vnto vs an exceeding and eternall weight of glorie. Both theſe two things <hi>S. Paul</hi> noteth in the generall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Chriſtes Churche, and alſo the Scripture teacheth the ſelfe ſame generall cauſes of the troubles of euery priuate mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt. As our Sauiour Chriſt repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the infirmitie of the borne blind man, which was for this cauſe, ſaieth he,<note place="margin">Iohn. 9.</note> that the workes of God ſhould be ſhewed on him. And in like caſe when Chriſt heard tell that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſicke, he ſaide. This ſicknes is not to death, but for the praiſe of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God might be praiſed there through. This did much ſet forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of God in Chriſt, that he was of power to rayſe vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:7840:45"/>
death a man, which had bin in his graue huri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 4. daies, &amp; was ſo corrupted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did ſtink. And wherin doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of God more exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dingly appeare to his glory, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in raiſing his church &amp; faithfull people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graue &amp; pit of troubles, afflictions, and many intolerable miſeries, wherin the worlde goeth about to treade them downe, &amp; burie them? Doth not Chriſt herein moſt marueilouſly ſet forth his glorie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the world by motion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil doth furiouſly fret &amp; rage againſt his faithful to roote out his word, then it ſpringeth &amp; flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth moſt plentifully, &amp; the faithful are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened &amp; confirmed therin moſt vnfainedly &amp; boldly? This hath God wrought in al ages in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fier of troubles &amp; afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, trying his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his own honours ſake &amp; their profit, as appeareth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtories of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning. And beſide this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our faith is thus tried, our patience proued, our hope co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by theſe afflictions, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue alſo diuers other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities &amp; profites by troubles which are more neceſſarie to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then either meate, or drinke: The worldly ones ſet more by their eaſy life here to ſerue their idle bellies, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the neceſſarie &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable things to eternal life. By troubles and afflictions the faithfull are made of like and
<pb facs="tcp:7840:45"/>
ſemblable ſhape to the Image of Gods own So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſt, ſaith <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> If they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with Chriſt, they ſhall liue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Whom the Lord loueth,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> him he chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, yea &amp; he ſcourgeth euery ſonne, whom he receiueth, &amp; nourtereth vs to that, which is profitable, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might receiue of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, that when we are afflicted, we are chaſtened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be damned with the world. Thus the ſcriptures do teach plainly &amp; alſo aboundantly, that for theſe two conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, God doeth ſuffer his church to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and his owne people in this worlde to be exerciſed vnder the croſſe: which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in all ages by the examples of all hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. For behold the face of Gods church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that good King <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto this our time, &amp; you ſhal ſee what wonderful chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges &amp; grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ouerthrowes his people haue ſuffred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, &amp; therefore ſhould not maruell of this our chaunge in England. After <hi>Dauid</hi> was anoynted King ouer Gods people, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 2. booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> declareth with what troubles God did exerciſe him, &amp; his whole kingdome du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his time. But he obſerued the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Lord, and kept the true religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people according to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="tcp:7840:46"/>
of God. After him <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> hath go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernance of Gods people; who in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his reigne walked after his Father <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Reg. 11.</note> did build Gods temple, and obſerued the true religion, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laſted but a while: for in his latter yeres he fell to idolatrie and the ſeruice of falſe gods, ſo that the true ſeruice of God began the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be corrupted. After him his ſonne <hi>Roboam</hi> reigned, at whoſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> realme had ſuch a miſerable chaunge, that it could neuer after recouer it ſelf again: for the kingdome was deuided, and 10. tribes which were called afterward <hi>Iſrael,</hi> fell from <hi>Roboam,</hi> &amp; from the true religion vnto ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, &amp; falſe ſeruing of God, &amp; ſo continued in falſe ſuperſticious religion, always hating the true ſeruice of God, killing the Prophets that did teach the trueth, &amp; the godly people that confeſſed the ſame many yeres: and yet al that time perſwaded them ſelues that they had the true ſeruice of God, and that their doings did much pleaſe God: yea the face of Gods Church was ſo blemiſhed and brought to ſuch a ſmal number of true profeſſors, that the Prophet <hi>Ely</hi> complaineth, that there was not one left, but he himſelfe alone, whoſe life alſo they ſought after. Conſider well this hiſtorie, and the working of God with his
<pb facs="tcp:7840:46"/>
Church &amp; true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Prophet <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> had taught the people the true ſeruice of God: the worthy king <hi>Dauid</hi> maintained the ſame all his time, but with great difficultie. <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne a Prince of moſt wiſdom and knowledge, perfectly inſtructed in the wayes of the Lorde, fell from God, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Gods religion with the falſe ſeruices inuented by man, ſo that the Lord was ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended therewith, that he cutte of from the rule of his poſteritie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: for the tenne tribes were neuer after him vnder the gouernance of his ſucceſſion, neither did afterwarde walke in the feare of God, but in Idolatrie and falſe religion, till at the laſt God ſent the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> to inuade them in that wiſe, that they ouercame them, caried them forth of their owne countrey, diſperſed them in many countreyes among the heathen, ſent ſtraungers to inhabite their land, and ſo vtterly deſtroyed that kingdom. God defende the realme of England from the like puniſhment. This was a fearfull iudgement of God, where hee had but one ſmal kingdome in the whole worlde, that bare the face of his Churche, where his true honour was maintained, and that ſo ſodainly of twelue tribes ten ſhould fal from God to
<pb facs="tcp:7840:47"/>
idolatrie, and falſe religion: yea and the other alſo, during all the time of <hi>Roboam,</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Abia</hi> after him, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> during al this time there was not in the worlde any Churche or people, where the ſyncere religion and pure word of God was receiued by publike autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and common order: although God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued always ſome that priuatly ſerued him and feared his Name faythfully, who were alwayes ſo hated and puniſhed by the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that their liues were bitter vnto them. In thoſe daies did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idolaters make the ſelfe ſame reaſons &amp; arguments againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and their doctrine, which your Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters doe make now againſt Gods people &amp; his true religion. The faithfull then liued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe Idolaters with no leſſe feare, trouble and perſecution, then the Chriſtians doe nowe in England. The Prophets were then impriſoned, &amp; driuen out of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey like ſeditious heretiks, the cauſers of all euill, as the true preachers now in England are partly impriſoned, partly driuen out of the realme. After the death of theſe wicked Kinges of <hi>Iehuda,</hi> God viſited his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with ſome light of the trueth by the meanes of <hi>Aza,</hi> and King <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> after him: who reſtored, although not perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:47"/>
the true religion, banniſhed the falſe, and deſtroyed the Altars of the Idolaters. The which reformation was not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great difficultie and trouble,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 22.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued but a ſmall time in that ſame order. For <hi>Ioram</hi> the ſonne of Kinge <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> ouerthrewe the true ſeruice of GOD, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it, and brought in the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſuperſtitions, and Idolatries of the Kinges of Iſrael, and ſo the Churche continued neuer perfectly reformed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes afflicted, till the time of <hi>Ezechias.</hi> For although <hi>Aza, Ioſaphat, Ioaz, Amazias, Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zias,</hi> and <hi>Ioatham,</hi> attempted a reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and were indifferently good Kinges, yet was not the Church cleanſed of all the Idolatries, and falſe counterfeit religion, as it appeareth by the Prophets, <hi>Ely, Amos, Eſay, Ozea, Micha.</hi> But the worthy King <hi>Ezechias</hi> in the firſt yere of his raigne began to reforme the religion, brake downe and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed all Idols and Images, hil altars, and whatſoeuer was againſt Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſtoring Gods true religion after the rule of Gods worde. The which thing as he brought to paſſe not without great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and difficulties, ſo it continued in puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie but a litle time. For his Sonne, wicked
<pb facs="tcp:7840:48"/>
               <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> who raigned after him, put away, and did forſake the true way, and brought in againe all maner of Idolatrie and falſe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and did grieuouſly puniſhe and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the faithfull people, and true Prophets. He ſhed (ſaith the Scripture) innocent bloud exceeding aboundantly. In lyke maner did his ſonne <hi>Ammon</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 21.</note> who raigned after him. This grieuous change remained thus, vntil the good King <hi>Ioſias</hi> made a newe and godly reformation: which ought to bee a glaſſe to all Princes to beholde themſelues in.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 22.</note> But this godly reformation of this good King did not continue: for his ſonne, and al the Kings of <hi>Iehuda</hi> after him forſooke the wayes of God, and reſtored againe the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, and falſe religion of their forefathers, and ſo continued, till God ſent the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> to deſtroye their citie, Temple, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. Who alſo led them captiue into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> where they continued many yeres in great affliction, as it appeareth by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Ieremie</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſo that in fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeres and aboue, in the dayes of all the Kinges of <hi>Iehuda</hi> Gods religion was ſet forth, and receiued in publike order ſyncerely and perfectly, and the contrarie vtterly bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; aboliſhed, but only in the times of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:48"/>
Ezechias</hi> and <hi>Ioſias:</hi> as <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> witneſſeth, ſaying, all Kings except <hi>Dauid, Ezechias</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> committed wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: for euen the Kings of <hi>Iehuda</hi> alſo forſooke the lawes of God. With what diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie and troubles, Gods religion and true ſeruice was reſtored after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> returne of Gods people from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and how ſhort a time it continued in puritie, what troubles and grieuous perſecutions the true ſeruants of the Lord ſuffered, it is partly ſet forth in <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah:</hi> after in <hi>Heſter,</hi> &amp; then in the <hi>Machabees:</hi> And although vnto the comming of Chriſt, there was an outwarde face and beautifull ſhew of Gods religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes, yet was it ſo defaced, and vtterly falſifyed with traditions of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, who were that time in eſtimation, that Chriſt himſelfe doth teſtifie, that their ſeruice was but vaine traditions of men,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> and the commaundement of God was not obſerued. All that time there were no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to inſtruct them in the right waye. For immediatly after the captiuitie, all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying ceaſſed in Iſrael. Nowe peruſe the hiſtorie of our Sauiour Chriſt in the foure Euangeliſtes, and you ſhall perceiue in what ſtate Chriſt founde his true religion, what
<pb facs="tcp:7840:49"/>
paines and trauaile he tooke to reſtore the true and ſyncere honouringe of God, with howe great difficultie hee brought it to paſſe, and at the laſt, howe it coſt hym his life. After whoſe death the crueltie of them, who would ſeeme to haue and maintaine the true honouring of GOD,<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> ceaſed not, but ſtirred moſt vehement perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true Churche of Chriſt, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed it thorowout all the worlde: with what paines, troubles, and difficultie true Chriſtianitie was planted, and falſe religion put away, <hi>S. Lucas</hi> partly mentioneth in the Actes of the Apoſtles, who ſpent their liues in the buylding of Chriſt his Church. After Chriſt his death the cruell tyrant <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperour did perſecute the Church moſt cruelly, after whoſe time, the Church was in ſome quiet, but not long: for <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperour did perſecute Chriſt his Church to deſtroye his true religion moſt hainouſly. <hi>Nerua</hi> his ſucceſſour was friendly to the Chriſtians. <hi>Traiane</hi> after him a cruell perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutour, and enemie: and then <hi>Hadriane:</hi> after whoſe tyme the Churche had reſt for a whyle. For ſhortly after, the Chriſtians that were in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and alſo in the Weſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were cruelly diſquieted. Shortly after
<pb facs="tcp:7840:49"/>
this tyme did England receyue the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth, and was the fyrſt countrey of all the world that receiued the faith of Chriſt by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique authoritie (<hi>Lucius</hi> beeing their firſt Chriſtian King,) but the puritie of Chriſt his trueth, did not long there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, not much aboue an hundreth yeres. <hi>Seuerus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour wrought all the meanes that might be, to deſtroy Chriſtes Churche, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte the true religion with moſt ſharpe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, after whoſe time there was ſome quiet: but ſhortly after the cruel tyrant <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> did ſore moleſt the faithfull, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe after him <hi>Detius, Gallus, Hoſtilianus, Lucius Valerianus. Galienus</hi> graunted the Chriſtians peace, <hi>Aurelianus</hi> did perſecute them. And <hi>Diocleſianus</hi> more like an infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſerpent, then an earthly man, did as it were deuoure the Church moſt cruelly. In this time was the greateſt perſecution, that had bene before: The tormentours were much more wearie in ſheading the Chriſtian bloud, and cruelly tormenting the faithfull, then the holy martyrs were in ſuffering the paines.<note place="margin">Euſebius eccle. hiſt. li. 8. cap. 9.</note> There were in this perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thirtie daies aboue ſeuenteene thouſand Chriſtians killed moſt ſpitefully. But <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the good Emperour became a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:50"/>
ſet the Church in peace, &amp; was the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> Emperour that did by publike authoritie put downe gentilitie, and truely mainteined the Chriſtianitie. But that laſted not long: for within ſhort time after, <hi>Iulianus th'apoſtata</hi> being Emperour, went about to vndo al that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had done, vſed wonderfull poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to deſtroy the Chriſtian religion, and did afflict the faithfull verie grieuouſly. After this time the Church was grieuouſly mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the <hi>Arrians,</hi> after with <hi>Hunnes, Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals,</hi> and <hi>Gothes,</hi> and ſo continued many yeres till all good learning began wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be decayed, and at the length albeit the Church ſeemed to be at reſt, yet hath it bene euen to this daye miſerably afflicted, and the pure religion vtterly defaced, by two vicars the Deuil put in commiſſion at one time about eight hundreth yeres ſince: the Antichriſt of Rome for the Weſt, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> for the Eaſt. Nowe weye and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with your ſelues this ſame briefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſall of the ſtate of Gods Churche, howe the Church of the Iſraelites was afflicted in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> then in the time of the Iudges, next vnder the Ringes, at the laſt caried into a ſtraunge countrey captiues, after their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and reedifying of the Temple what
<pb facs="tcp:7840:50"/>
great perils and troubles it ſuſtained till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the dayes of the <hi>Machabees,</hi> next conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hiſtorie of Chriſt, &amp; the Actes of the Apoſtles. After this the ten notable perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Church ſuffered vnder moſt cruell tyrantes from the eight yere of <hi>Nero,</hi> by the ſpace of three hundreth and twenty yeres, vnto the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and from his time three hundreth yeres after by the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> and barbarous <hi>Hunnes, Vandals</hi> and <hi>Gothes,</hi> by whoſe meanes good learning was decaied, and ignorancie brought in: And then marke with aduiſement, how that from that time hitherto <hi>Mahomet</hi> hath vſurped and afflicted the Eaſt Church, and the Pope the weſt (for he began to exerciſe his proude power ouer the Churche about the ſame time, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> brought in his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) conſyder I ſaye with aduiſement in all theſe times, howe litle whyle Gods religion was mainteined in the Churche, what perilous chaunges were in the kingdomes, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eeeding crueltie was alwayes vſed againſt the people of God, as though they had bene heretikes, his word condemned as hereſie, and the cauſe of all euils: and you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that this is no newe or vnkoth thing, that the true religion of God ſhould be thus
<pb facs="tcp:7840:51"/>
put away and condemned, and the faithfull Churche moleſted and afflicted both gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as is plaine in theſe hiſtories, and alſo particularly in the miniſters &amp; faithful mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as appeareth in <hi>Abel,</hi> the Patriarches, Prophets, Chriſt, his Apoſtles, &amp; in a great number of holy ſainctes and martyrs, ſince the death of Chriſt til nowe our daies. Thus may you plainely ſee how God hath wrought with his Church at all times, and therefore ſhould not diſcourage your ſelues, becauſe of this ſodain chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, but with <hi>Dauid</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging your ſinnes to God, declare vnto him how many they be, that vexe you, and riſe againſt you, naming you heretikes and the children of <hi>Belial,</hi> as they named <hi>Dauid.</hi> Let the wicked Idolaters boaſt and bragge that they haue ouercome you, and that God hath giuen you ouer &amp; wil no more be your God: let them put their truſt in <hi>Abſalom</hi> with his long golden lockes, and in the wiſedome of <hi>Achitophel</hi> the wiſe counſailour, yet ſay you with <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou O Lord art my defender, thou art my worſhip, and the lifter vp of my head, feare not their violence to hurt you in your bodies, to harme you in your goodes. Perſwade your ſelues with <hi>Dauid</hi> that the Lord is your defender, who hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed you
<pb facs="tcp:7840:51"/>
round about, and is as it were a ſhielde, that doeth couer you on euery part: it is he only that may and will compaſſe you about with glorie and honour, it is hee, that will thruſt downe thoſe prowde hypocrites from their ſeat, and exalt his lowly and meeke. <hi>Dauid</hi> in the mids of his miſeries did thus comfort him ſelfe, leaning to the prouidence of God, looking for deliuerance from him, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God no time, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting the whole matter vnto his wiſedome and goodneſſe. He layed him ſelfe to ſleepe, roſe againe, was not afrayed for innumerable people, that ſet him round about to haue deſtroyed him, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord wil ſuſtaine me, ſaieth this good King. This was his ſhot anker, here was his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, herewith he comforted himſelfe, that the Lord would bee his defender and ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, and at the length reſtore him to his place againe. He armed him ſelfe with the armour of God,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> but aboue al he tooke to him the ſhield of faith, wherewith he quenched the fyrie dartes of the wicked. Hee had the helmet of ſaluation, the ſworde of the ſpirit, the promiſes of God, and buckled theſe faſt vnto him ſelfe with this long and durable girdle of faithfull prayer and watching, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I wil crye vnto the Lord with my voyce,
<pb facs="tcp:7840:52"/>
and he will heare me from his holy hill. If you will receiue comfort, crye with <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto the Lorde, exerciſe your faith in earneſt and continual prayer, ſay, ariſe O Lord &amp; help me, and he will ſmite your enemies on the cheekebone, and braſt all their teeth in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he will hang vp <hi>Abſalom</hi> by his owne long heare. <hi>Achitophel</hi> through deſperation ſhall hange him ſelfe, the bandes ſhalbe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; you deliuered: for this belongeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to ſaue his fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their enemies, &amp; to bleſſe his people. Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> in the mids of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction did comfort him ſelf, truſt to the only prouidence of his moſt mercifull God, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading himſelfe both of his good will, and mightie power, whereby he ſhould haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, and was not deceiued. This bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſhall alſo be on you, if that neglecting the wiſdome of the worlde, you ſubmit your ſelues to the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God your heauenly Father, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully crying him mercie, &amp; patiently abiding his good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7840:52"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
